welcome back to success $0.99 artificial
欢迎回归成功 $ 0.99人工
general intelligence today we have
我们今天的一般情报
Stephen Wolfram Wow
斯蒂芬沃尔夫勒姆哇
that's the first I didn't even get
这是我第一次没有得到的
started you're already clapping in his
开始你已经鼓掌了他的
book a new kind of science he has
预订他所拥有的一种新科学
explored and revealed the power beauty
探索并揭示了权力之美
and complexity of cellular automata as
和细胞自动机的复杂性
simple computational systems for which
简单的计算系统
incredible complexity can emerge it's
令人难以置信的复杂性可以出现
actually one of the books that really
其实一本书 真的
inspired me to get into artificial
激励我进入人工
intelligence he's created the Wolfram
情报他创造了Wolfram
Alpha competition knowledge engine
阿尔法竞争知识引擎
created Mathematica that has now
创建了现在的Mathematica
expanded to become Wolfram language both
扩展成为Wolfram语言
he and his son were involved in helping
他 和 他的儿子 参与了帮助
analyze create the alien language from
分析创建一个从外星语言
the movie arrival of which they use the
他们使用的电影到来了
Wolfram language please again gives
Wolfram语言请再次给出
Steven a warm welcome boy so I gather
史蒂文是一个热情的欢迎 男孩，所以我聚集
the brief here is to talk about how
这里简要的谈谈 如何
artificial general intelligence is going
人工智能正在进行中
to be achieved is that they set the
要实现的是他们 设定了
basic picture so I maybe I'm reminded of
基本的图片， 所以 我 可能会被提醒
kind of a storage I don't think I've
一种存储的 ，我 不认为我已经
ever told in public but that something
曾经 在 公共场合 讲过 但 有些事
that happened just a few buildings over
那只发生在 几座建筑物上
from here so this was 2009 and Wolfram
从这里开始，这是2009年和Wolfram
Alpha was was about to arrive on the
阿尔法即将抵达
scene I assume most of you have used
场景我假设大多数 人 都使用过
wolf now for a scene wolf alpha yes the
狼现在为 一个场景狼阿尔法是的
how many of you've used wolf alpha ok
你们有多少人使用过狼阿尔法 OK
that's good so I had long been a friend
这很好，所以我一直是朋友
of Marvin Minsky's and Marvin was a sort
Marvin Minsky和Marvin是一种
of pioneer of the AI world and I kind of
AI世界的先驱和我有点儿
seen for years you know question
看多年 你就知道 问题
answering systems that tried to do sort
回答试图 排序的系统
of general intelligence question
一般情报问题
answering and so at Marvin and so I was
在马文回答， 所以我是
going to show Marvin you know Wolfram
要告诉马文，你知道 沃尔夫勒姆
Alpha he looks at it and he's like okay
阿尔法他看着它，他很好
that's fine whatever said no Marvin this
无论如何 说没有马文 这个 都没关系
time it actually works
它确实有效的时间
you can try real questions this is
你可以试试这个真正的问题
actually something useful this is not
实际上这有用的东西不是
just a toy and it was kind of
只是一个玩具，它有点像
interesting to see it took took about
有趣的 是看到 花了很长时间
five minutes for Marvin to realize that
马文五分钟意识到这一点
this was finally a
这终于是了
to an answering system that could
到一个可以的回答系统
actually answer questions that were
实际上回答的问题
useful to people and so one question is
对人们有用 ，所以一个问题是
how did we how do we achieve that so you
我们是如何实现这一目标的呢 ？
know you go to Wolf's malphur and you
知道你和 狼的马弗和你 一起去
can ask it I mean it's I don't know what
可以问我的意思是我不知道 是什么
we can ask it I don't know what's the
我们可以问它我不知道是什么
some random question what is the
一些随机问题是什么
population of Cambridge actually here's
剑桥人口 居然在这里
a question / let's try that what's the
一个问题/让我们尝试一下
population of Cambridge is probably
可能是剑桥人口
going to figure out that we mean
要弄清楚 ，我们的意思
Cambridge Massachusetts it's going to
剑桥马萨诸塞州即将到来
give us some number it's gonna give us
给我们一些它 会给 我们的数字
some plot actually what I want to know
一些情节实际上是我想知道的
is number of students at MIT divided by
麻省理工学院的学生人数除以
population of Cambridge see if it can
剑桥人口看看它是否可以
figure that out and okay it's kind of
想出来， 好吧就是这样
interesting right oh no that's / ah
有趣的哦哦没有那个/啊
that's interesting a guest that we were
我们这是一个有趣的 客人
talking about Cambridge University as
谈论剑桥大学
the as the denominator there so it says
它就是那里的分母
the number of students at MIT divided by
麻省理工学院的学生人数除以
the number of students at Cambridge
剑桥大学 的学生人数
University that's interesting I'm
大学，我很有意思
actually surprised let's see what
实际上很惊讶让我们看到了什么
happens if I say Cambridge MA there now
如果我现在说剑桥MA 那就会发生
as it probably fail horribly no that's
因为它可能会失败 不 可怕 那是
that's good okay so no that's
那很好，所以没有
interesting that's a plot as a function
有趣的是，这是一个函数的情节
of time of the fraction of the of okay
时间的分数好的
so anyway so I'm glad it works the so
所以无论如何所以我很高兴这样做
one one question is how did we manage to
一个问题是我们是如何做到的
get so that many things have to work in
得到 许多东西必须工作
order to get stuff like this to work you
为了得到这样的东西 的工作，你
have to be able to understand the
必须 能够理解
natural language you have to have that
你必须拥有 自然语言
data sources you have to be able to
您必须能够 获得的数据源
compute things from the data and so on
从数据中计算东西等等
one of the things that was a surprise to
那是一个惊喜的事情之一
me was in terms of natural language
我是在自然语言方面
understanding was the critical thing
理解是 至关重要的事情
turned out to be just knowing a lot of
原来只是知道了很多
stuff the actual pausing of the natural
填充 自然的实际暂停
language is kind of I think it's kind of
语言是 一种我认为这是一种
clever and we use a bunch of ideas that
聪明，我们使用一堆想法
came from my new kind of science project
从我的新的 科学项目 来了
and so on but I think the most important
等等， 但我认为 最重要的
thing is just knowing a lot of stuff
事情就是了解 很多 东西
about the world is is really important
关于 世界是非常重要的
to actually being able to to understand
实际上能够理解
natural language in a useful situation I
在有用的情况下自然语言我
think the other thing is having
认为另一件事就是
actually having access to lots of data
其实有 机会获得 大量的数据
let me show you a typical example here
让我 在这里 告诉你一个 典型的例子
of what is needed so I asked about the
需要什么，所以我问 了 一下
ISS and hopefully it'll wake up and tell
国际空间站，希望它能唤醒并告诉我们
us something here come on what's going
我们这里发生了 什么事情
on here there we go okay so it figured
在这里，我们 没事， 所以它想通了
out that we probably are talking about a
我们可能在谈论一个
spacecraft not a file format and now
飞船不是一种文件格式， 现在
it's going to give us a plot that shows
它会给我们一个 显示 的情节
us where the ISS is right now so to make
我们 ISS现在 在哪里 这样做
this work we obviously have to have some
这项工作我们显然必须有 一些
feed of you know radar tracking data
您知道雷达跟踪数据
about satellites and so on which we have
关于我们拥有的卫星等
for every satellite that's that's out
对于那些已经出局的卫星
there but then that's not good enough to
有 ，但那么这是不是足够好
just have that feed then you also have
只是有饲料，那么你也有
to be able to do celestial mechanics to
能够 做天体力学
work out well where is the ISS actually
实际上ISS在哪里工作得很好
right now based on the orbital elements
现在基于轨道要素
that have been deduced from radar and
这是从雷达和雷达推断出来的
then if we want to know things like okay
然后，如果我们想知道 好的 事情
when is it going to it's not currently
什么时候到目前为止
visible from Boston Massachusetts it
从波士顿马萨诸塞州可见
will next rise at 7:30 6:00 p.m. on
将于下午7 点 30 分起床
Monday on today so you know this
星期一今天所以你 知道这一点
requires a mixture of data about what's
需要关于什么的数据的混合
going on in the world together with
与世界一起继续前进
models about how the world is supposed
关于世界如何被假设的模型
to work being able to predict things and
工作 能预测 的东西，
so on and I think another thing that
等等，我认为 另一件事
kind of realized about about AI and so
关于人工智能等的实现
on from the wolfman alpha effort has
从狼人 阿尔法努力
been that you know one of the earlier
是你知道的早一个
ideas for how one would achieve AI was
关于如何实现AI的想法是
let's make it work kind of like brains
让我们让它像大脑一样工作
do and let's make it figure stuff out
做，让我们把它弄清楚
and so if it has to do physics let's
所以，如果它必须做物理， 那就让我们 这样做 吧
have it do physics by pure reasoning
让它通过纯粹的推理来做物理学
like you know people at least used to do
就像你知道人们 至少习惯做的那样
physics but in the last 300 years we've
物理学，但在过去的 300年里，我们已经
had a different way to do physics that
有一种不同的物理方式
wasn't sort of based on natural
不是基于自然的
philosophy it was instead based on
它取而代之的是哲学
things like mathematics and so one of
像数学 这样的东西
the things that we were doing in in
我们正在 做 的事情
Wolfman alpha was to kind of cheat
狼人阿尔法是一种欺骗
relative to what had been done in
相对于 什么都 在 做了
previous AI systems which was instead of
以前的AI系统而不是
using kind of reasoning type methods
使用一种 推理类型的方法
we're just saying okay we want to
我们只是说我们想要的
compute where the ISS is going to be
计算国际空间站的位置
well we've got a bunch of equations of
好吧，我们有 一堆方程式
motion that corresponds to differential
与差异相对应的运动
equations we're just going to solve the
方程，我们只是 要 解决
equations of motion and get an answer
运动方程并 得到答案
that's kind of leveraging the last 300
这 是利用过去的300
years or so of
年左右 的
of exact science that have been done
已经完成的精确科学
rather than trying to make use of kind
而不是 试图 利用善良
of human reasoning ideas and I might
人类推理的想法，我可能
might say that in terms of the the
可以说， 在该条款
history of the wolf malphur project when
狼马尔弗项目的历史何时
I was a kid a disgustingly a long time
很长一段时间，我还是一个令人作呕 的孩子
ago I was interested in AI kinds of
以前我 对 AI种类 很 感兴趣
things and I in fact I was kind of upset
事实上，事实上，我有点不高兴
recently to find a bunch of stuff I did
最近找了一堆 我做过 的东西
when I was 12 years old kind of trying
当我12 岁那种尝试
to assemble a pre version of Wolfram
组装Wolfram的预版本
Alpha way back before it was
Alpha方式回来之前
technologically possible but it's also a
技术上可行，但它也是一个
reminder that one just does the same
提醒人们，一个刚刚做 同样的
thing once whole life so to speak at
曾经一生都可以说的事情
some level um but what happened was when
某种程度，但发生的事情是什么时候
when I am I started off working mainly
我什么时候开始主要工作
in physics and then I got involved in
在物理学中， 然后 我被卷入
building computer systems to do things
建立计算机系统 来做事
like mathematical computation and so on
喜欢数学计算等
and I then sort of got interested in
而我则有点有了兴趣 在
okay so can we generalize this stuff and
好的，我们可以概括这些东西
can we can we really make systems that
我们能真正制造出那样的系统吗？
can answer sort of arbitrary questions
可以回答任意问题
about the world and for example sort of
关于世界和 排序 的 例子
the the the the promise would be if
承诺将是 如果
there's something that is systematically
系统地有一些东西
known in our civilization make it
在我们的文明中知道它
automatic to answer questions on the
自动回答的问题
basis of that systematic knowledge and
系统知识 和基础
back in the in around late 1970s early
早在20世纪70年代末期就回来了
1980s my conclusion was if you want to
20世纪80年代我的结论是， 如果你想
do something like that the only
做那样的事情
realistic path to being able to do it
能够做到这一点的现实路径
was to build something much like a brain
是 建立 一个像大脑一样的东西
and so I got interested in neural nets
所以我对神经网络感兴趣
and I tried to do things with neural
我试着用神经来做事
nets back in 1980 and nothing very
在1980年退网，并没有什么
interesting happened well I couldn't get
有趣的发生得 很好，我无法得到
him to do anything very interesting and
他做任何非常有趣的事情
that um so I kind of had the idea that
这嗯 让我有种有 想法
that the only way to get the kind of
唯一 的 方式来获得的那种
thing that now exists in alpha for
现在存在 于 alpha中的东西
example was to build a brain like thing
例如，建立一个像大脑一样的东西
and then many years later for reasons I
然后很多年后因为我的原因
can explain I kind of came back to this
可以解释 我有点回到 这里
and realized actually it wasn't true
并意识到实际上并非如此
that you had to build a brain like
你必须建立 像大脑一样的大脑
things sort of mere computation was
事情有点像计算
sufficient and that was kind of what got
足够的， 这是什么得到的
me started actually trying to build
我开始真正尝试 建立
Wolfram Alpha when we started building
我们开始建设时的 Wolfram Alpha
wolf malphur one of these I did was go
狼马尔弗其中一个我做的是去
to a sort of a field trip to a big
到一个大的实地考察
reference library and you know you see
参考图书馆，你知道你看到了
all these shelves of books and so on and
书所有这些货架等 以及
the question is can we take all of this
问题是我们可以 采取所有 这些
knowledge that exists in all of these
所有 这些中存在的知识
books and actually automate being able
书籍实际上是自动化的
to answer questions on the base
在基础 上 回答 问题
Javad and I think we've pretty much done
贾瓦德 和 我认为我们已经 做了 很多
that for that at least the books you
那至少是你的书
find in a typical reference library so
在一个典型的参考图书馆找到
that was it looked kind of daunting at
这是它看上去有点令人生畏 在
the beginning because it's this there's
一开始，因为就是这样
a lot of knowledge and information out
大量的知识和信息
there but actually it turns out there
但实际上它就在那里
are a few thousand domains and we've
是几千个领域 ，我们已经
steadily gone through and worked on
稳步走过并继续努力
these different domains another feature
这些不同的域名另一个 特征
of the worth mouthful project was that
这个值得满口的项目是那样的
we didn't really you know I've been
我们真的不知道我去过
involved a lot in doing basic science
在 做 基础 科学方面 涉及很多
and in trying to have sort of grand
并试图有一点盛大
theories of the world one of my
世界理论之一
principles in building Wolfram Alpha was
建立Wolfram Alpha的原则是
not to start from a grand theory of the
不要从一个宏大的理论开始
world that is not to kind of start from
世界不是一种 开始
some global ontology of the world and
世界和世界的一些全球本体论
then try and build down into all these
然后尝试建立所有这些
different domains but instead to work up
不同的领域，而是努力工作
from having you know hundreds then
从你让你知道数百
thousands of domains that actually work
成千上万的实际工作域名
whether they're you know information
无论 他们是你 知道的信息
about cars or information about sports
关于汽车或有关体育的信息
or information about movies or whatever
或有关电影或其他的信息
else how each of these domains sort of
否则每个域如何排序
building up from the bottom in each of
从 每个人 的底部建立起来
these domains and then finding that
这些领域 ，然后发现
there were common themes in these
有共同的主题 ， 这些
domains that we could then build into
域 ，我们可以 再建 成
frameworks and then sort of construct
框架然后排序构造
the whole system on the basis of that
在此基础上整个系统
and that's kind of that's kind of how
这就是 那种方式
its worked and I can talk about some of
它工作，我可以谈谈 一些
the actual frameworks that we end up
我们最终 的实际框架
using and so on but maybe I should
使用等等 但也许我应该
explain a little bit more so so one
稍微解释一下
question is how does how does Wolf's
问题是沃尔夫是怎么做 的
mouth actually sort of work inside and
嘴巴实际上 是里面的工作
the answer is it's a big program it's
答案是这是一个很大的程序是
about it's the core system is about 15
关于它的核心系统大约是15
million lines of Wolfram language code
百万行Wolfram语言代码
and it's some number of terabytes of raw
这是一些 TB的原始数据
data and so the the way the thing that
数据等事情的方式
sort of made building wolf now for
现在为了制作狼
possible was this language wolf and
可能是这种语言狼和
language which started with Mathematica
从Mathematica开始的语言
which came out in 1988 and has been sort
它出现在1988年，并且 已经排序了
of progressively growing since then so
从那以后逐渐增长
maybe I should show you some things
也许我 应该告诉你一些事情
about both language and and you know
关于语言和你知道的
it's easy you can you know use this mit
很容易你知道使用这个mit
has a site license for it you can use it
有一个站点许可证， 你可以使用它
all over the places you can find it on
你 可以在各处找到它
the web but cetera etc etc but okay
网络，但cetera等等，但 没关系
the basics work the let's let's start
基础工作让我们开始吧
off with something like let's make a
用一些东西 来制作一个
random graph and let's say we have
随机图，让我们说我们有
a random graph with two hundred nodes
一个有200个节点的随机图
400 vertices okay so there's a random
400个顶点 没关系，所以有一个随机的
graph a first important thing about
图表 是第一个重要的事情
wolfing language is it's a symbolic
狼语言是一种象征性的
language so I can just pick up this
语言，所以我可以拿起这个
graph and I could say you know I don't
图表，我可以说你知道我没有
do some analysis of this graph that
对此图进行一些分析
graph is just a symbolic thing that I
图只是我的象征性事物
can just do computations on oh I could
我可以做就好了
say let's let's get a another good thing
说让我们让另一件好事
to always do is get a current image see
总是做的就是 当前图像 看
there we go and now I could go and say
我们 去，现在 我可以去说
something like let's let's do some basic
像让我们做一些基本的事情
thing let's say let's edgy detect that
让我们说让我们的前卫检测到这一点
image again this this image is just a a
再次形象这个图像 只是一个
thing that we can manipulate we could
我们可以操纵的东西
take the image we could make it I don't
拍摄我们可以制作的图像我没有
know we could take the image and
知道我们可以 拍摄图像
partition it little pieces do
分割它的小块 做
computations on that I don't know simple
对我的计算我不知道简单
let's do let's just say sort each row of
让我们只是说排序的每一行
the image assemble the image again
图像 再次 组合 图像
whoops assemble that image again we'll
我们将再次 组装那个图像
get some some mixed up picture there if
得到一些一些混合起来的画面，如果有
I wanted to I could for example let's
我想我可以 举例说
say let's make that the current image
说让我们把它当成图像
and let's say make that dynamic now I
让我们说现在让我充满活力
can be just running that code hopefully
可能只是 希望 运行该 代码
and little loop and there we can make
和小循环，我们可以做
that work so the you know one one
这工作所以你知道一个人
general point here is there's you know
总的来说，这就是你知道的
this is just an image for us is just a
这只是 我们的一个图像 仅仅 是 一个
piece of data like anything else if we
像 我们 一样的数据
just have a variable a thing called X it
只需要一个名为X的变量
just says okay that's X I don't need to
只是说 可以，XI 不需要
know particular value it's just a
知道特别的价值它只是一个
symbolic thing the corresponds to that's
象征性的东西对应于 那个
a thing called X now you know what gets
一个名为X的东西现在你知道得到了什么
interesting when you have a symbolic
当你有 一个象征性的 时候很有趣
language and so on is we're interested
语言等等我们感兴趣
in having it represent stuff about the
在拥有 它代表有关的东西
world as well as just abstract kinds of
世界以及抽象的世界
things that many you know I can
很多你知道我能做的事情
abstractly say you know find some funky
抽象地说你知道找到一些时髦
integral I don't know what you know
积分我不知道你知道什么
that's then representing using symbolic
然后代表使用符号
variables to represent algebraic kinds
用来表示代数种类的变量
of things but I could also just say I
但我也可以说 我
don't know something like Boston and
不知道像波士顿这样的东西
Boston is another kind of symbolic thing
波士顿是另一种象征性的东西
that has if I say what what is it really
如果我真的说出它是什么， 那就有了
inside that's it's the
在里面就是这样的
today a City Boston Massachusetts United
今天是一个城市 波士顿麻省联合
States actually noticed when I type that
当我输入时，各国实际注意到了
in I was using natural language to type
在我用自然语言打字
it in and it gave me a bunch of
它在，它给了我一堆
disambiguation here it said assuming
在这里消除歧义说它假设
Boston is a city assuming Boston
波士顿是假设波士顿城市
Massachusetts use Boston New York or
马萨诸塞州使用波士顿纽约或
okay there's let's use let's use Boston
好吧，让我们使用让我们使用波士顿
and the Philippines which I've never
和菲律宾，我从来没有
heard of but but um let's try using that
听说但是我们试着用它
instead and now if I look at that it'll
而不是现在 如果我 看着 它会
say it's Boston in some province of the
说它是 波士顿的一些 省份
Philippines etc etc now I might ask it
菲律宾等等我 现在 可能会问它
of that I could say something like
的，我可以这样说
what's the population of that and it um
什么是人口，它 嗯
okay it's a fairly small place or I
好吧，这是一个相当小的地方或我
could say for example let me let me do
可以说比如我让 我做
this let me say a geo list plot from
这让我说 一个地理列表图
that Boston
那个波士顿
let's take from that Boston - and now
让我们从那个波士顿- 现在
let's type in Boston again and now let's
让我们再次在波士顿打字，现在让我们来吧
have it used the default meaning of the
它使用了 默认的含义
word of Boston and then let's join those
波士顿的话，然后让我们加入那些
up and now this should plot this should
现在这应该是应该这样做的
show me a plot there we go okay so
给我看一个情节，我们一点也没关系
there's the path from the Boston that we
有来自波士顿的路径，我们
picked in the Philippines to the Boston
在菲律宾挑选到 波士顿
here oh we could ask you don't know I
在这哦，我们可以问 你 不知道我
could just say I could ask it the
可以说我 可以问它
distance from one to another or
从一个到另一个的距离或
something like that so the the one of
像那样的东西
the things here one things we found
这里的 东西我们 发现 了 一件事
really really useful actually in
真的有用 实际
language was first of all there's a way
语言首先 是一种方式
of representing stuff about the world
代表关于世界的东西
like cities for example or let's say I
比如城市 或让我们说我
want to say let's let's do this let's
我想说让我们这样做吧
say let's do something with cities let's
说让我们对城市做点什么吧
say capital cities in South America okay
说南美洲的首府城市还可以
so notice this is a piece of natural
所以注意这是一块 自然的
language this will get interpreted into
语言将被解释为
something which is precise symbolic
一些精确的象征性的东西
wolfram language code that we can then
我们可以用 wolfram语言代码
compute with and that will give us the
用和计算会给我们带来的
citizens out the capital cities in South
公民 在南方的首都城市
America I could for example let's say I
美国我可以举个例子 来说我
say find shortest to US and I'm going to
说找到最短的美国，我要去
use some some oops no I don't want to do
使用一些oops不，我不想做
that what I want to do first is to say
我想先做的就是说
show me the geo positions of all those
告诉我所有这些的地理位置
cities on line 21 there so now it will
21号线的城市现在就这样了
find the geo positions and now it will
找到地理位置，现在它会
say compute the shortest tour
说计算最短的旅游
so that's saying there's a 10,000 mile
所以说有一万英里
traveling salesman tour around those
旅行推销员游览那些
cities so I could take those cities were
城市，所以我可以采取这些城市
on line 21 and I could say order the
在第21行，我可以说顺序
cities according to this and then I
根据这个城市然后我
could make another geo list plot of that
可以使 另一个地理名单情节
join it up and this should now show us a
加入它，现在应该向我们展示一个
traveling salesman tour of the of the
的旅行商旅游
capital cities in South America um so
南美洲的首府城市
you know it's it's sort of interesting
你知道这是 这有点 有趣
to see what's involved in making stuff
看看制作东西有什么用
like this work the one of you know my my
喜欢这项工作 ，你们其中一个人都知道我的
goal has been to sort of automate as
目标一直是自动化
much as possible about things that have
多地 了解 事情有
to be computed and that means knowing as
被 计算，这意味着知道为
many algorithms as possible and also
尽可能多的算法
knowing as much data about the world as
寂寂世界 尽可能 多的数据
possible and I kind of view this as sort
可能，我认为 这是 排序
of a knowledge-based programming
基于知识的编程
approach where you have you know a
你知道 的方法
typical kind of idea in programming
典型的一种 编程思想
languages is you know you have some
语言你知道你有一些
small programming languages has a few
小编程语言有一些
primitives that are pretty much tied
原始人非常 紧密
into what a machine can intrinsically do
进入 机器本能做什么
and then maybe you'll have libraries
然后也许你会有图书馆
that add on to that and so on
添加到那个 等等
my kind of crazy idea of many many years
我多年来的疯狂想法
ago has been to build an integrated
以前一直在建立 一体化
system where all of the stuff about
系统所有的东西都在
different domains of knowledge and so on
不同的知识领域 等
are all just built into the system and
都刚刚建立在系统中
and designed in a coherent way I mean
我的意思是以连贯的方式设计
this has been kind of the story of my
这一直是同类产品 中 的 故事 我
life for the last thirty years is trying
过去三十年的 生活 正在努力
to keep the design of the system
保持系统的设计
coherent even as one adds all sorts of
即使有人添加各种各样的内容也是连贯的
different areas of of capability so as
不同的能力范围如此
some I mean we can go and dive into all
有些我的意思是我们可以深入了解所有人
sorts of different kinds of things here
各种 不同性质的 东西 在这里
but maybe as an example well let's do
但也许作为一个例子，让我们做
what could we do here we could take come
我们能在 这做什么，我们可以接受
let's try how about this is that a bone
让我们试试这是一个骨头
I think so that's a bone so let's try
我认为这是一个骨头让我们试试
that as a mesh region see if that works
作为网格区域， 看看是否有效
so this will now use a completely
所以这 将完全使用
different domain of human endeavor okay
人类 努力的 不同领域 好吧
oops there's two of those bones let's
哎呀，那里有两块 骨头
try let's just try them let's try
试试让我们尝试一下吧
humorous let's try the that the mesh
幽默让我们尝试 网格
region for that and now we should have a
那个区域， 现在我们应该 有一个
bone here okay there's a there's a
骨头在这里 好吧那里有一个
representation of a bone let's take that
骨骼的表示让我们接受
bone and we could for example say let's
骨头，我们可以说，让我们
take the surface area of that as in some
取的是 ， 表面区域 中的一些
some units or I could let's do some much
有些单位或者我可以做些什么
more outrageous thing let's say we take
更令人发指的事情让我们说
region distance so we're going to take
区域距离所以我们要 采取
the distance from some from that bone to
从一些 骨头 到 骨头的距离
a point let's say 0 0 Z and let's make a
一个点让我们说0 0 Z，让我们做一个
plot of that distance with Z going from
这个 距离 的情节以Z 从去
let's say I don't have no idea where the
比方说，我没有不知道的地方
where the spawn is but let's try
产卵的地方， 但让我们 试试
something like this so that was really
像这样的东西 真的
boring um let's try them so what this is
无聊嗯，让我们尝试一下 这有啥
doing again a whole bunch of stuff has
再做一大堆的东西了
to work in order for this to operate
工作以使其 运作
this has to be this is a this is some
这必须是这是一个
region in 3d space that's represented by
3d空间中由...表示的区域
some mesh you have to compute you know
你需要 计算 一些 你知道的 网格
do the computational geometry to figure
做了计算几何推测
out where it is if I want it to let's
如果我想要让它出现在哪里
try anatomy anatomy plot 3d and let's
尝试解剖解剖图3d 和让我们
say something like left hand for example
比如用左手说些什么
and now it's going to show us probably
现在它 可能会向我们展示
the complete data that it has about the
它有关于的完整数据
geometry of the left hand there we go ok
左手的几何形状我们就好了
so there's there's the results and we
所以有结果 和我们
could take that apart and start
可以把它分开并 开始
computing things from it and so on so
从中计算东西等等
what um so this this is some so there's
什么， 所以这 是一些所以有的
a there's a lot of kind of computational
有很多种计算方法
knowledge that's built in here one let's
这里建立的知识就是让我们的
talk a little bit about kind of the
谈一点关于同类产品中
modern machine learning story so for
现代机器学习的故事 所以
instance if I say let's get a picture
例如，如果我说让我们拍照
here let's say um let's let's just say
在这里，让我们说，让我们说吧
picture of symbol got a favorite kind of
符号的图片得到了最喜欢的一种
animal what's Panda okay so let's try ok
动物什么是 熊猫好吧让我们试试吧
giant panda
大熊猫
okay okay there's a panda let's see what
还好 还好 有一个熊猫让我们来看看
now let's try saying um let's try for
现在让我们试着说，让我们试试吧
this panda let's try saying image
这只 熊猫让我们尝试说出形象
identify and now here we'll be
确定，现在我们将在这里
embarrassed probably but let's just see
可能很尴尬，但让我们看看
let's see what happens if I say image
让我们看看如果我说图像会发生什么
identify that and now it'll hopefully
确定这一点，现在它有希望
wake up wake up wake up this only takes
醒来醒来醒来 这只需要
a few hundred milliseconds
几百毫秒
okay very good giant panda let's let's
好吧非常 好的大熊猫让我们来吧
see what it's we'll see what the
看看它是什么我们会看到什么
runners-up were to the giant panda let's
让大熊猫队获得亚军
say we want to say the ten runners-up in
说我们想说 十个亚军
all categories for that thing okay so a
这个东西的所有类别都可以
giant panda a prop here Ned which I've
大熊猫这里的支柱是我的Ned
never heard of are pandas carniverous
从来没有听说过大熊猫的 气味
ate bamboo shoots okay so that was so
吃竹笋 好吧就是这样
lucky I didn't get that one it's really
幸运的是我没有 得到 它真的
sure it's a mammal and it's absolutely
确定它是一种哺乳动物， 绝对是
certain it's a vertebrate okay so you
确定它是一种脊椎动物，所以你
might ask how did it figure this out and
可能会问这是怎么想出来的
so then you can kind of look under the
那么你可以看看下
hood and say so we have a whole
引擎盖说，所以我们有一个整体
framework for representing neural nets
表示神经网络的框架
symbolically and so this is the actual
象征性地这是实际的
model that it's using to do this so this
它正在使用的模型这样做
is a so there's a neural net and it's
这是一个神经 网络，它是
got we can drill down and we can see
我们可以向下钻取，我们可以 看到
there's there's a piece of the neuron
那里有一块神经元
that we can drill down even further to
我们可以进一步向下钻取
one of these and we can probably see
其中之一， 我们可以看到
what that's a batch normalization layer
什么是批量标准化层
somewhere deep deep inside the entrails
在内脏深处的某个地方
of the not panda but of this thing okay
在没有熊猫 的 ，但这个 东西好吗
so now let's take that object which is
所以现在让我们把那个对象拿走
just a symbolic object and let's feed it
只是一个象征性的对象，让我们喂它
the picture of the Panda and we can see
我们可以看到熊猫的照片
and there oops I was not giving it the
在那里oops 我没有给 它
right thing what did I just do wrong
正确的事 我做错了 什么
here okay let's let's take our isolated
这里好吧让我们把我们的孤立
okay let's take this thing and feed it
好吧，让我们拿 这个东西喂它
the picture of the Panda and it says a
熊猫的照片， 它说了一个
giant panda okay how about we do
大熊猫好吧 我们怎么样
something more outrageous let's take
让我们更加离谱的事情
that neuron that and let's only use the
那个神经元，让我们只使用它
first let's say 10 layers of the neuron
首先让我们说 10层 神经元
that so let's just take out 10 layers of
那就让我们 拿出10层
the neuron that's and feed it the Panda
神经元是 熊猫的神经元
and now what we'll get is something from
现在我们得到的是来自的东西
the insides of the neuron that and I
我和 神经元的内部
could say for example let's just make
可以说比如让我们做
those into images okay so that's what
那些进入图像没关系，这就是什么
that's what the neuron that
这就是那个神经元
had figured out about the Panda after 10
在 10 岁之后就已经想到了熊猫
layers of going through the neuron that
通过神经元的层次
and maybe actually be interesting to see
也许实际上 很有趣
let's do a feature space plots and now
让我们来做一个特征空间图
we're going to of those intermediate
我们要去那些中间人
things in the sort of in the brain of
在大脑中的东西
the neuron that sort of speak this is
那个说这个的神经元是
now taking so what this is just doing is
现在这样做是为了做到这一点
to do dimension reduction on this space
在这个空间做降维
of images and so it's not very exciting
图像， 所以它不是很令人兴奋
it's probably mostly distinguishing
它可能主要是区分
these by total gray level but that's
这些是总灰度，但那是
kind of showing us the space of of
那种向我们展示的 空间
different ton of different sort of
不同种类 的 不同种类
features of the insides of the Shinra on
神罗 内部的特征
that so it's also what's interesting to
那 所以它也有什么有趣的
see here is things like the symbolic
看到这里是象征性的东西
representation of the neuron that's and
这是 神经元 的代表性和
if you if you're wondering how does that
如果你 想知道那 是 怎么回事
hatch will work inside it's underneath
舱口盖将 在其下方工作
it's using a max net which we happen to
它正在使用我们碰巧遇到的最大网络
have contributed to a lot and there's
已经做出了很多贡献
sort of a bunch of symbolic layers on
一堆符号层
top of that that feed into that and
最重要的是进入那个 和
maybe I can show you here let me show
也许我可以告诉你这里让 我表现出来
you how you would train one of these
你你会怎么训练 的其中 之一
neural nets that's also kind of fun so
神经网也很 有趣
we have a data repository that has all
我们有一个拥有所有数据存储库
sorts of useful data one piece of data
各种有用的数据的 一个 数据 片 的
it has is a bunch of neuron that
它有一堆神经元
training sets so this is a standard emne
训练集所以这是一个标准的emne
straining set of handwritten digits
紧张的手写数字集
okay so there's m missed and you notice
好吧，所以我 错过了 你注意到了
that these things here that's just an
这些东西 在这里 只是一个
image which i could copy out and i could
我可以复制出来的图像， 我可以
do you know let's say I could do color
你知道吗，我说我可以做颜色
negate on that image because it's just
否定该图像，因为它只是
an image and there's there's the results
一个图像，有结果
and so on and now I could say let's take
等等， 现在我可以说让我们接受
let's take a neuron that like let's take
让我们 采取一个 像我们一样 的神经元
a simple neuron that like Linette for
像Linette一样的简单神经元
example okay so let's take Linette and
例如没关系，让我们来看看Linette和
then let's take the untrained initial
然后让我们采取未经训练的初始
evaluation Network so this is now a
评估网所以现在这是一个
version of Linette simple standard
Linette简易标准版
neural nets that didn't get trained so
没有接受过训练的神经网络
for example if I if I take that that
例如，如果我 接受那个
symbolic representation of Lynette and I
Lynette和我的象征性代表
could say net initialize then it will
可以说net初始化然后它会
take that and it'll just put random
接受它，它只会随机
weights into Lynette okay so if I take
如果我服用的话，可以 加入Lynette吧
those random weights and I feed it a
这些随机的重量和我喂 它
zero here I feed it that image of a zero
零在这里 我把它的形象喂给零
it will presumably produce something
它可能会产生一些东西
completely random in this particular
这个特别完全随意
case - right so now now what I would
案件- 现在就是现在我想做的事情
like to do is to take this so that was
喜欢这样 做就是 这样
just randomly initializing the weights
只是随机初始化权重
so now what I'd like to do is to take
所以现在我想做的就是 采取
the emne straining set and I'd like to
emne straining set和我想
actually train Lynette using MMS
实际上 使用MMS 训练 Lynette
training set so let's take let's take
训练集让我们采取让我们采取
this and let's take a random sample of
这个，让我们随机 抽样
let's say I don't know a thousand pieces
让我说我不知道​​一千块
of Lynette come on why is it having to
丽奈特的加油为什么它不必
load it again there we go okay so
再次装入那里，我们去 好了，
there's a there's a random sample there
那里有一个随机样本
was on line 21 and now let me go down
在第21行，现在让我走下去
here and say where was it well look we
在这里，说这里是 很好看我们
can just take this this thing here so
我可以在这里 拿 这个东西吧
this is the uninitialized version of
这是未初始化的版本
Lynette and we can say take that and
丽奈特，我们可以说拿 和
then let's say net train of that with
然后让我们说网络列车
the thing on line 21 which was that
第21行就是那件事
thousand instances so now what it's
一千个实例， 所以现在它是什么
doing is its running training on and
正在做的是它的 运行训练
that's you see the loss going down and
那是你看到的损失
so on it's running training for for
所以在它的运行训练
those thousand instances of Lynette and
那一千个Lynette和
it will we can stop it if we want to
如果我们愿意 ， 我们可以阻止它
actually this is a new display this is
其实这是一个新的显示 ，这是
very nice
非常好
this is this is a new version of both
这是两者的新版本
languages is coming out next week which
语言 下周现身 其中
I'm showing you but it's quite similar
我告诉你，但它非常相似
to what exists today but because that's
对于今天存在的东西，但因为那是
one of the features of running a
的 运行的 特征之一
software company is that you always run
软件公司是你经常运行的
the the very latest version of things
最新版本的东西
for better or worse and that's and this
无论好坏，这就是这个
is also a good way to debug it because
也是调试它的好方法，因为
supposed to come out next week if I find
如果我发现，下周应该出来
some horrifying bug maybe it will get
一些可怕的bug也许会得到
delayed but let's try them let's sum
延迟， 但让我们尝试他们的 总和
let's try this okay now it says it's
让我们试试这个好吧现在就说它了
zero okay
零好的
and so so this is now a trained version
所以现在这是一个训练有素的版本
of Lynette trained with that with that
Lynette的训练就是那个
training data um one of the things so
训练数据 微米的事情之一 ，所以
you know we can talk about all kinds of
你知道我们可以谈论各种各样 的
details of your mats and so on but maybe
你的垫子的细节等等但也许
I should zoom out to talk a little bit
我应该缩小谈一点点
about bigger picture as I see it so one
关于更大的图片，因为我看到它如此
question is sort of a question of what
问题是 什么 的 问题
is in principle possible to do with
原则上可以做到
computation so you know we have as we're
计算所以你知道我们就像我们一样
you know we're building all kinds of
你知道我们正在建造各种各样 的
things we're making image identifies
我们正在做的图像识别的东西
we're figuring out those kinds of things
我们正在搞清楚那些事情
about where the International Space
关于国际空间的位置
Station is and so on question is what is
车站等问题是什么
what is in principle
什么是原则上的
possible to compute and so the you know
可以计算，所以你知道
one of the places one can ask that
人们 可以 问的 其中一个地方
question is when one looks at for
问题是当一个人在寻找
example models of the natural world one
自然界的示例模型之一
can say you know how do we make models
可以说你知道我们如何制作模特
of the natural world kind of a a
自然界的 一种 aa
traditional approach has been let's use
传统方法已经被使用了
mathematical equations to make models of
数学方程， 使车型
the natural world a question is if we
自然界是一个问题，如果我们
want to kind of generalize that and say
想要概括一下并说出来
well what are all possible ways to make
还有什么都是可能的办法， 使
models of things what can we say about
事物的模型我们可以说什么
that question so I spent many years of
这个 问题，所以我花了很多年 的
my life trying to address that question
我的生活试图 解决 这个问题
and basically what what I've thought
基本上 我的想法是什么
about a lot is that if you want to make
很多是 如果你想做的
a model of a thing you have to have
你必须 拥有 的东西的模型
definite rules by which the thing
事物的明确规则
operates what's the most general way to
操作 最通用的 方式
represent possible rules well in today's
在 今天 很好地代表了可能的规则
world we think of that as a program so
世界我们 认为这 是一个 程序
the next question is well what does the
接下来的问题是好什么 是
space of all possible programs look like
所有可能程序的空间看起来像
and most of the time you know we're
而且大多数时候你都知道我们
writing programs like Wolfen language is
写沃尔芬语的程序是
50 million lines of code and it's a big
5000万行代码 ，这是一个很大 的代码
complicated program that was for built
用于构建的复杂程序
for a fairly specific purpose but the
为了一个相当特定的目的但是
question is if we just look at sort of
问题是，如果我们只是看一下
the space of possible programs more or
可能的程序 空间 更多或
less at random what's out there in the
更 随意的是什么在那里
space of possible program so I got an
可能的 程序 的 空间 ，所以我得到了一个
interest in many years ago in cellular
多年前 在蜂窝电话中的 兴趣
automata which are a really good example
自动机是一个 很好的 例子
of a very simple kind of program so let
一个 非常简单 的程序，所以 让
me show you an example of one of these
我给你看一个这样的例子
so this is these are the rules for a
所以这是这 对一个规则
typical cellular automaton and this just
典型的细胞自动机，这只是
says you have a row of black and white
说你有一排黑色和白色
squares and this just says you look at a
广场，这只是说你看一个
black a look at a square say what color
黑色看一个方形说什么颜色
is that square what color left or it's
是那个正方形是什么颜色或它的颜色
left and right neighbors decide what
左右邻居决定什么
color the square will be on the next
方块的颜色将在下一个
step based on that rule okay so really
基于该规则的步骤确实如此
simple rule so now let's let's take a
简单的规则 所以现在让我们来看看吧
look at what what actually happens if we
看看如果我们实际发生了什么
use that rule a bunch of times so we can
多次使用该规则，以便我们可以
take that rule the 254 is just the
采取这个规则254只是
binary digits that correspond to those
与那些对应的二进制数字
positions in this rule so now I can say
现在我可以说 ， 这条规则中的 立场
this I could say let's do 50 steps let
我可以说让我们做50步
me do this sum and now if I run
我做这 一笔，现在如果我 跑
according to the rule I just defined it
根据我刚刚定义的规则
turns out to be pretty trivial it's just
事实证明这是 非常微不足道 的
saying if any if any square is if we
如果有的话，如果有的话，我们就说
start off with a black square if any
如果有的话，从黑色方块开始
square is if any neighboring square is
square是相邻的广场
black make a black square so we've we've
黑色是一个黑色的方块，所以我们就是这样
used a very simple program
用了一个非常简单的程序
we've got a very simple results out okay
我们得到了一个非常简单的 结果
let's try a different program we can try
让我们尝试一下我们可以尝试的其他程序
changing this we'll get some that's a
改变这个我们会得到 一些 ，这是一个
program with one bit different now we
现在我们有一点不同的程序
get that kind of pattern so the question
得到那种模式所以问题
is well what happens you might say okay
很好， 你可能会说 好的
if you've got such a trivial program
如果你有这样一个微不足道的计划
it's not surprising you're just going to
你刚刚去，这并不奇怪
get Trevor a results out so but you can
得到Trevor的结果，但你可以
do an experiment to test that hypothesis
做一个实验来检验 这个假设
you can just say let's take all possible
你可以说让我们尽一切可能
programs there are 256 possible programs
程序有256个可能的程序
that are based on these eight bits here
这是根据 此处 这些 八位
let's just take well let's just whoops
让我们 好好让我们呐喊吧
let's just take come let's say the first
让我们来看看第一个
64 of those programs and let's just make
64个这样的程序，让我们来做
a echo let's just make a table of the
回声 让我们只是制作一张表
results that we get by running those
我们通过运行那些得到的结果
first 64 programs here so here we get
这里有前64个程序， 所以我们得到了
the result and what you see is well most
结果和 你看到的是最好的
of them are pretty trivially the lake
他们非常琐碎的湖泊
they start off with one black cell in
他们从一个黑色的细胞开始
the middle and it just tools after one
中间，它只是一个又一个的工具
side occasionally we get something more
偶尔我们会得到更多的东西
exciting happening like here's a nice
令人兴奋的事情发生在这里是一个很好的
nested pattern that we get if we were to
嵌套的模式，我们得到，如果我们 要
continue it longer it would it would
它会延长它的时间
make you know more detailed nesting but
让你知道更详细的嵌套但是
then my all-time favorite science
然后我最喜欢的科学
discovery if you go on and just look at
发现，如果你去的， 只是看
these after a while you find this one
经过一段时间你会找到这个
here which is rule 30 in this in this
这里是第30条在这 在这
numbering scheme and that's doing
编号方案，这正在做
something a bit more complicated you say
你说的东西有点复杂
well what's going on here you know we
那么你 知道 我们 发生了什么
just started off with this very simple
刚刚开始 这么 简单
rule let's see what happens maybe after
规则让我们看看之后会发生什么
a while you know if we run rule 30 long
有一段时间 你知道 我们是否长期执行规则30
enough it will resolve into something
足够它会解决某些问题
simpler so let's try running it let's
更简单所以让我们尝试运行吧
say 500 steps and that's the whoops
说500步，这就是呐喊
that's the result we get I'd say let's
这就是我们得到的结果我会说让我们
just make it fullscreen okay
只是让它 全屏好吧
it's aliasing a bit on the projector
它在投影机上有点混淆
there but but you get the basic idea
但是你得到了基本的想法
this is a so this just started off from
这是 一个 刚开始的
one black cell at the top and this is
顶部有一个黑色电池， 这 是
what it made and that's pretty weird
它做了什么，这很奇怪
because all this is you know this is
因为这一切都是你知道 的
sort of not the way it's supposed things
有点不是它所谓的事情
are supposed to work because what we
应该工作，因为我们
have here is just that little program
这里有 一个小程序
down there and it makes this big
在那里，这使得这个很大
complicated pattern here and you know we
复杂的模式在这里，你知道我们
can see there's a certain amount of
可以看到有一定数量 的
regularity on one side but for example
在一侧上的规律性，而是 例如
the center column
中心栏
this pattern is for all practical
这种模式适合所有人
purposes completely random in fact it
其实目的完全是随意的
was reused as a random number generator
被重用为 随机数 发生器
in Mathematica and Wolfram language for
在Mathematica和 Wolfram语言中
many years it was recently retired after
多年后它最近退休了
after excellent service because we found
经过优质服务，因为我们发现
a somewhat more efficient one um
一个更有效的一个嗯
the but the so you know what do we learn
但是你知道我们学到了什么
from this what we learn from this is out
从中我们从中学到 了 什么
in the computational universe of
在计算宇宙
possible programs it's possible to get
可能的程序是可能的
even with very simple programs very rich
即使非常简单的程序非常丰富
complicated behavior well that's
复杂的行为， 那么这
important if you're interested in
如果你有兴趣，这很重要
modeling the natural world because you
因为你塑造自然界
might think that there are programs that
可能会认为 有 程序
represent systems in nature that might
代表可能的 自然系统
work this way and so on it's also
以这种方式工作，等等
important for technology because it says
对技术很重要，因为它说
ok let's say you're trying to find a
好吧，让我们说你正试图 找到一个
let's say you're trying to find a
让我们说你正试图找到 一个
program that's a good random number
程序是一个很好的 随机数
generator how are you going to do that
发电机你打算怎么做
well you could start thinking very hard
以及你可以开始 苦苦思索
and you could try makeup you know you
你可以试 妆，你知道你
could try and write down all kinds of
可以尝试写下各种各样的
flowcharts about how this random number
关于这个 随机数 如何的流程图
generator is going to work or you can
发电机是去 工作 ，或者你 可以
say forget that I'm just going to search
说忘了我要去 搜索
the computational universe for possible
可能的计算世界
programs and just look for one that
程序，只是寻找 一个
serves as a good random number generator
作为一个好的随机数发生器
in this particular case after you've
在你这个特殊情况下
searched 30 programs you'll find one
搜索了30个程序，你会找到一个
that makes a good random number
这是一个很好的随机数
generator why does it work that's a
发电机为什么它的工作原理 ，这是一个
complicated story it's not a story that
复杂的故事，这不是一个故事
I think necessarily we can really tell
我想我们一定能说出来
very well but what's important is that
非常好，但重要的是
this is this idea that out in the
这是这个想法说出来的
computational universe there's a lot of
计算宇宙有很多
rich sophisticated stuff that can be
可以是丰富复杂的东西
essentially mind for our technological
基本上关注我们的技术
purposes that's the important thing
目的是重要的
whether we understand how this works is
我们是否理解这是如何工作的
a different matter I mean it's like when
一个不同的问题我的意思是它就像什么时候
we look at the natural world the
我们来看看 自然界
physical world were used to kind of
物理世界习惯 了
mining things you know we started using
挖掘你知道我们开始使用的东西
magnets to do magnetic stuff long before
磁铁早就做磁性的东西
we understand understood the theory of
我们理解理解理论
ferromagnetism and so on and so
铁磁性 等等
similarly here we can sort of go out
同样在这里，我们可以出去
into the computational universe and find
进入计算世界并找到
stuff that's useful for our purposes now
现在 对我们的目的 很有用的东西
in fact the world of sort of deep
事实上这个世界有点深刻
learning and neural nets and so on is a
学习和神经 网络等是一个
little bit like this it uses the trick
它 有点像这样 使用技巧
that there's a certain degree of
有一定程度 的
differentiability there so you can kind
那里的可分性让你可以善良
of home in on let's try and find
在家里让我们试着找
something that's incremental II better
这是增量II更好的东西
and for certain kinds of problems that
和某些类型的问题 ，
works pretty well
效果很好
I think the thing that we've done a lot
我认为我们已经做了很多事情
I've done a lot it's just sort of
我已经做了很多， 只是一点点
exhaustive search in the computational
详尽的搜索计算
universe of possible programs just
只是可能程序的宇宙
search of trillion programs and try and
搜索万亿计划并尝试和
find one that does something interesting
找一个有趣的东西
and useful for you um there's a lot of
对你有用，你有很多
things to say about what well actually
事实上要说些什么
in in these search of trillion programs
在这些 万亿计划的 搜索中
and find one that's useful let me show
并找到一个有用的让我展示
you another example of that um see so I
你的 另一个 例子 嗯 看到，所以我
was interested a while ago in the I have
我刚才感兴趣了
to look something up here sorry um in C
看的东西在这里不好意思 嗯 用C
in boolean algebra and in I was
在布尔代数和我是
interested in in the space of all
对所有人 的空间感兴趣
possible mathematic says um and let me
可能的数学说，嗯， 让我
just see here I I'm not finding what I
只是看到 我在 这里， 我 找不到我
wanted to find sorry I was a good
想找个抱歉我很好
example I should have memorized this but
例如 我应该记住这一点但是
I haven't so um there we go there it is
我不是那么 我们去那里
um so I was interested in if you just
嗯，所以我对你感兴趣
look at so we talked about sort of
看看我们谈到的那种
looking at the space of all possible the
看着所有可能 的 空间
space of all possible programs another
所有可能的节目的空间另一个
thing you can do is say if you're going
如果你要去，你可以做的就是说
to invent mathematics from nothing what
从无到有发明数学
possible axiom systems could be used in
可能的公理系统可以用于
mathematics so I was curious where do
数学所以我好奇在哪里
and that again might seem like a
而这似乎又像是一个
completely crazy thing to do to just say
只是 说， 完全 疯狂的事情
let's just start enumerate axiom systems
让我们 开始 列举公理系统
at random and see if we find one that's
随机，看看我们是否找到了一个
interesting and useful but it turns out
结果很有趣但很有用
once you have this idea that out in the
一旦你有这个想法，那就在了
computational universe or possible
计算宇宙或可能
programs there's actually a lot of
程序实际上有很多
low-hanging fruit to be found it turns
低悬的水果被发现 它变成了
out you can apply that in lots of places
你可以在很多 地方 申请
I mean the thing to understand is why
我的意思是要理解的是为什么
why do we not see a lot of engineering
为什么我们没有看到 很多工程
structures that look like this the
看起来像这样的结构
reason is because our traditional model
原因是因为我们的传统模式
of engineering has been we engineer
工程学 一直 是我们的工程师
things in a way where we where we can
我们在哪里 可以 做到的事情
foresee what the outcome of our
预见的结果是什么我们
engineering steps are going to be and
工程步骤都将 是 和
when it comes to something like this we
当涉及到这样的事情时， 我们
can find it out in the computational
可以在计算中找到它
universe what we can't readily foresee
我们不能轻易预见的宇宙
what's going to happen we can't do sort
什么会发生，我们不能做排序
of a step by step design
一步一步的设计
of this particular thing and so in
这个特别的东西 等等
engineering and human engineering as
工程与人类工程学
it's been practiced so far most of it
到目前为止 ，它已被大部分实践
has consisted of building things where
包括建筑物在哪里
we can foresee step by step what the
我们可以一步一步地预见到了 什么
outcome of our engineering going to be
我们的工程成果将会如此
and we see that in programs we see that
我们在程序中看到了这一点
in other kinds of engineering structures
在其他类型的工程结构中
and so there's sort of a different kind
所以有一种不同的 类型
of engineering which is about mining the
关于开采的 工程
computational universe of possible
可能的计算宇宙
programs and it's worth realizing
程序，值得实现
there's a lot more that can be done a
还有更多 可以做的事情
lot more efficiently by mining the
通过挖掘更有效率
computational universe of possible
可能的计算宇宙
programs than by just constructing
程序而不仅仅是构建
things step by step as a human so for
事情一 步步作为人类如此
example if you look for optimal
例如，如果你寻找最佳
algorithms for things like I don't know
对于我不知道的事情的算法
even something like sorting networks the
甚至像排序网络这样的东西
optimal sorting networks look very
最佳分拣网络看起来 非常
complicated they're not things that you
复杂的他们不是你的事
would construct by sort of step-by-step
将逐步构建
thinking about things with in a kind of
在一种思考事情
in a kind of typical human way and so
以一种典型的人性化方式等等
this this idea you know if you're really
这个想法你知道，如果你真的
going to have computation work
有 计算工作
efficiently you are going to end up with
你会有效地结束
these programs that are sort of just
这些程序有点公正
mined from the computational universe
从计算 宇宙中挖掘出来的
and one of the issues with mining things
和 采矿事物 的 问题 之一
so they're there this makes use of
所以他们在那里利用
computation much more efficiently than a
计算比a更有效
typical thing that we might construct
我们可能构建的 典型事物
now one feature of this is it's hard to
现在这个的一个特点就是很难
understand what's going on and there's
明白这是怎么回事 ，并有
actually a fundamental reason for that
实际上是一个根本原因
which is in our efforts to sort of
这是我们努力 的排序
understand what's going on we get to use
了解我们将要使用的是什么
our brains our computers our mathematics
我们的脑子我们的计算机是我们的数学
or whatever and our goal is this this
或者其他什么，我们的目标就是这个
particular little program did a certain
特别是小程序 确实做到 了
amount of computation to work out this
解决这个问题 的计算量
pattern the question is can we kind of
模式 问题是我们可以
outrun that computation and say oh I can
超出计算并说 哦我可以
tell that actually this particular bit
实际上告诉那个特殊的位
down here is going to be a black black
在这里将是一个黑色的黑色
bit you don't have to go and do all that
位你不必去尽一切
computation but it turns out that then
计算，但事实证明
again this will maybe as a digression
再次， 这可能 是一个题外话
which which there's this phenomenon I
哪个有这种现象我
call computational irreducibility which
呼叫计算不可约其
i think is really common and it's a
我认为这很常见，而且是一个
consequence of this thing I call
我打电话给这件事的结果
principle of computational equivalence
计算等价原理
and that the principle of computational
而且计算原理
equivalence basically says as soon as
等价基本上只要说
you have a system whose behavior isn't
你有一个行为不是的系统
fairly easy to analyze the chances are
很容易分析的机会
that the computation it's doing is
它正在进行的计算是
essentially as sophisticated as it could
基本上尽可能复杂
be and that has consequences like it
是的， 这有 它的 后果
implies that the typical thing like
意味着 典型的东西一样
this will correspond to a universal
这将对应一个普遍的
computer that you can use to program
可以用来编程的电脑
anything it also has the consequence of
什么它也有后果
this computational irreducibility
这种计算不可约性
phenomenon that says you can't expect
说你不能指望的现象
our brains to be able to outrun the
我们的大脑能够逃脱 的
computations that are going on inside
计算所 里 想 的
the system if there was computational
系统 是否有 计算
reducibility then we can expect that
然后我们可以期待这种可还原性
this thing went to a lot of trouble and
这件事遇到了很多麻烦
did a million steps of evolution but
做了一百万步的进化 但是
actually just by using our brains we can
实际上 只是通过使用 我们的大脑我们可以
jump ahead and see what the answer will
跳到前面，看看答案会是什么
be computational irreducibility suggests
是计算不可约性建议
that isn't the case if we're going to
如果我们要去，情况就不是这样
make the most efficient use of
最有效地 利用
computational resources we will
计算资源我们会
inevitably run into computational
不可避免地遇到 计算问题
irreducibility all over the place it has
它的所有地方都是不可减少的
the consequence that we get the
我们得到的后果
situation where we can't readily sort of
我们不能随便排序的情况
foresee and understand what's going to
预见并了解将要发生的事情
happen so back to mathematics for a
发生了如此回到数学的一个
second so this is just an axiom system
第二，所以这只是一个公理系统
that so I looked for all possible look
所以 我寻找所有可能的外观
through sort of all possible axiom
通过一切可能的公理
systems starting off with very really
系统从非常真实开始
tiny ones and I asked the question
很小的，我问了这个问题
what's the first axiom system that
什么是第 一个公理系统
corresponds to boolean algebra so it
对应于布尔代数所以它
turns out this this thing here this tiny
事实证明，这件事情在这里很小
little thing here generates all theorems
这里的小事生成所有定理
of boolean algebra it is that it is the
布尔 代数是它的
simplest axiom for boolean algebra now
现在布尔代数最简单的公理
something I have to show you this
我必须向你展示 这一点
because it's a new feature you see they
因为它是一个新的功能，你看 他们
um if I say find equation or proof let's
嗯，如果我说找到方程或证明让我们
say I want to prove commutativity of the
说我想证明交换性
NAND operation I'm going to show you
NAND操作我将告诉 你
something here this is going to try to
这里的东西会尝试
generate let's see if this works this is
生成让我们 看看这是否有效
going to try to generate an automated
试图生成自动化
proof based on that axiom system of that
基于那个公理 系统的证明
result so it had 102 steps in the proof
结果因此 在证明中 有 102个步骤
and let's try and say let's look at for
让我们试着 说让我们 来看看吧
example the proof network here actually
例如证明网络 实际上 这里
let's look at the proof data set um now
让我们来看看证明数据集庵 现在
that's not what I wanted I should learn
这不是我想要的， 我应该学习
how to use this shouldn't I um let's see
如何 使用这个不应该我嗯让我们来看看
what I want is the you know proof data
我 想是的，你知道的证明资料
set there we go very good ok so this is
设置在那里我们 非常好，所以这是
actually let's let's say first of all
实际上让我们先说吧
let's say the proof graph ok so this is
让我们说证明图是好的，所以这是
going to show me the how that proof was
告诉 我 这个证据是怎么回事
done so
这样做了
they're a bunch of lemmas that got
他们是一堆得到的外阴
proved and from those lemmas those
证明了那些从那些外表那些
lemmas were combined and eventually it
lemmas结合起来，最终结合起来
proved the result so let's let's take a
证明了结果，让我们来看看
look at the let's take a look at what
看看让我们来看看是什么
some of those llamas were okay so here's
其中一些美洲驼很好，所以这里
the results so after so it goes through
结果如此经过
and these are various lemmas it's using
这些 是它正在使用的各种引理
and eventually after many pages of
并最终经过多页
nonsense it will get to the result okay
胡说八道它会得到结果没关系
each one of these some of these llamas
这些骆驼中的每一个都是这些
are kind of complicated there that's
那里有点复杂
that's that llama it's a pretty
这就是那只 美丽的骆驼
complicated lemma etc etcetera etcetera
复杂的引理等等等
so you might ask what on earth is going
所以你 可能会问到底是怎么回事
on here and the answer is so I first
在这里，答案就是我第一个
generated a version of this proof 20
生成了 此证明的 一个 版本 20
years ago and I tried to understand what
几年前，我试图 了解 什么
was going on and I completely failed and
是 怎么回事，我就 彻底失败了 ，
it's sort of embarrassing because this
这是因为这种尴尬
is supposed to be a proof it's supposed
应该是它应该的证据
to be you know demonstrating some
你是否知道展示一些
results and what we realize is that you
结果和我们意识到的是你
know what does it mean to have a proof
知道有 证据 是什么意思
of something what does it mean to
这是什么意思
explain how a thing is done you know
解释你知道怎么做的事情
what is the purpose of a proof purpose
证明目的的目的是什么？
of a proof is basically to let humans
一个证明基本上是让人类
understand why something is true and so
明白为什么事情是真的等等
for example if you go to let's say we go
例如， 如果你去说我们走了
to wolf now fur and we do you know some
狼现在毛皮，我们你知道一些
random thing where we say let's do you
随便我们说让我们 做你 的 事情
know an integral of something or another
知道某种或 另一种的整体
it will be able to very quickly in fact
事实上它很快就能实现
it will take it only milliseconds
它只需要几毫秒
internally to work out the answer to
在内部找出答案
that integral okay but then somebody
那个 积分还好，但后来有人
whose wants to hand in a piece of
谁愿意交出一块
homework or something like that needs to
家庭作业或类似的东西 需要
explain why is this true okay well we
解释为什么这是真的好我们
have this handy step-by-step solution
有这个方便的逐步解决方案
thing here which
这里的东西
explains why it's true now the thing I
解释为什么现在我的确如此
should admit about the step-by-step
应该承认有关 一步一步
solution is it's completely fake that is
解决方案是完全假的
the steps that are described in the step
步骤中描述的步骤
by step solution have absolutely nothing
一步到位解决方案 绝对没有
to do with the way that internally that
与 内部 的方式 有关
integral was computed these are steps
积分计算这些是步骤
created purely for the purpose of
纯粹是为了这个 目的而创造的
telling a story to humans about why this
讲述一个 关于为什么这个 故事 给人类
integral came out the way it did and now
积分以它 现在 的方式出现了
what we're seeing and so that's a so
我们所看到的，所以就是这样
that's one thing is knowing the answer
这是 一件事是知道 的答案
the other thing is being able to tell a
另一件事是能够告诉 一个
story about why the answer worked that
关于为什么答案有效的故事
way
办法
well what we see here is this is a proof
我们在这里看到的是这是一个证据
but it was an automatically generated
但它是自动生成的
proof and it's a really lousy story for
证明，这是一个非常 糟糕的故事
us humans I mean if it turned out that
我们的人类， 我的意思是，如果 事实证明
one of these theorems here was one that
这些定理 的一个 在这里是一个
had been proved by Gauss or something
已经被高斯证明了什么
and appeared in all the textbooks we
并出现在 我们 所有的 教科书中
would be much happier because then we
因为那时我们会更快乐
would start to have a kind of human
将开始 有一种 人
representable story about what was going
关于将要发生什么的可表示的故事
on instead we just get a bunch of
相反， 我们只是得到一堆
machine generated lemmas that we can't
机器生成的引理，我们不能
understand that we can't kind of wrap
明白我们不能那种 包装
our brains around and it's sort of the
我们的大脑周围，它是那种
same thing that's going on in when we
同样的事情发生在我们的时候
look at when these neural nets we're
看看我们这些神经网络 的时间
seeing you know when we were looking
看到你知道我们什么时候看
wherever it was at the innards of that
无论在哪里，它都在那里
neuron that and we say well how is it
神经元是我们说好了是怎么 回事
figuring out that that's a picture of a
弄清楚那是一张照片
panda well the answer is it decided that
熊猫很好的答案是它决定了
you know if we humans were saying how
你知道我们人类是怎么说的
would you figure out if it's a picture
你会弄清楚它是不是一张照片
of panda we might say well look and see
熊猫我们可能会说好看看
if it has eyes that's a clue for whether
如果它有眼睛是否是一个线索
it's an animal look and see if it's
这是动物的样子， 看看 它是不是
looks like it's kind of round and furry
看起来像圆形和毛茸茸的
and things that's a version of whether
和 事物是否是
it's a panda and Len cetera etcetera
它是一只熊猫和Len cetera等
etcetera but what it's doing is it
等等， 但它正在 做的是它
learnt a bunch of criteria for you know
你知道了很多标准
is it a panda or is it one of 10,000
它是熊猫还是10000只熊猫之一
other possible things that it could have
其他可能的事情， 它可能有
recognized and it learnt those criteria
认识到并且它学会了这些标准
in a way that was somehow optimal based
以某种方式最佳的方式
on the training that it got and so on
关于它所获得的训练等等
but it learnt things which were
但它学会了那些东西
distinctions which are different from
优其是 来自 不同
the distinctions that we humans make in
我们人类所做出的区分
the language that we as humans use and
我们作为人类使用的语言和
so in some sense you know when we start
所以在某种意义上你知道我们何时开始
talking about will describe a picture we
谈论将描述 我们的图片
have a certain human language for
有一定的人类语言
describing that picture we have you know
描述我们你知道的那张照片
in our human in typical human languages
在 人类的典型 人类语言中
we have maybe thirty to fifty thousand
我们可能有三十到五万
words that we use to describe things
我们用来描述 事物的词
those words are words that have sort of
这些话是有几分话
evolved as being useful for describing
演变为有用于描述
the world that we live in
我们生活的世界
um when it comes to there's known that
嗯，当涉及到还有的 了解，
it could be using it could say well that
它可以使用它 可以说好
the words that it is effectively learnt
它是有效学习的词
which allow it to make distinctions
这使它可以做出区分
about what's going on in the in the
关于在...中发生了什么
analysis that it's doing it has
它正在做的 分析
effectively invented words that describe
有效地发明了描述的词
distinctions but those words have
区别， 但那些话有
nothing to do with our historically
与我们的历史无关
invented words that exist in our
发明了 我们的文字
languages so it's kind of an interesting
语言所以它有点有趣
situation that that it is its way of
这是它的方式的情况
thinking so to speak if you say well
如果你说得好，可以这么说
what's it thinking about how do we
它是怎么想的我们是怎么做的
describe what it's thinking that's a
描述它的想法 是 什么
tough thing to answer because just like
很难回答， 因为就像
with the with the automated theorem
与自动化定理
we're we're sort of stuck having to say
我们有点不得不 说
well we can't really tell a human story
好吧，我们无法真正讲述人类的故事
because the things that it invented are
因为它发明的东西是
things for which we don't even have
我们甚至没有的东西
words in our languages and so on okay so
我们的语言中的 单词 等等
one thing to realize is in this kind of
要 意识到的一件事就是在这种情况下
space of sort of all possible
所有可能的空间
computations there's a lot of stuff out
计算有很多东西
there that can be done there's this kind
那里可以 做到这一点
of ocean of sophisticated computation
精密 计算 的 海洋
and then the question that we have to
然后 我们要 问的问题
ask for us humans is okay how do we make
问我们人类是好的我们怎么做
use of all of that stuff so what we've
使用所有这些东西，所以我们
got kind of on the one hand is we've got
有一方面我们得到了
the things we know how to think about
我们知道如何思考的 事情
human language is our way of describing
人类语言是我们描述的方式
things our way of talking about stuff
我们讨论东西的方式
that's the one one set of things the
那是一个一组的东西
other set of things we have is this very
我们拥有的其他一切都是这样的
powerful kind of seething ocean of
强大的沸腾的海洋
computation on the other side where lots
计算在另一边的地段
of things can happen so the question is
事情可能会发生， 所以问题是
how do we make use of this sort of ocean
我们如何利用这种海洋
of computation in the best possible way
以最好的 方式计算
for our human purposes and building
为了我们的人类目的和建设
technology and so on and so the the way
技术等等 的方式
I see you know my kind of part of what
我知道你知道我的一部分
I've spent a very long time doing is
我花了很 长时间做的
kind of building a language that allows
建立一种允许的语言
us to take human thinking on the one
我们把人类思考放在一个人身上
hand and describe and sort of provide a
手和描述和提供一个
sort of computational communication
一种计算通信
language that allows us to get the
允许我们获得 的语言
benefit of what's possible over in the
是什么 在可能超过利益
sort of ocean of computation in a way
某种方式的计算海洋
that's rooted in what we humans actually
这根植于我们人类 实际上的东西
want to do and so I kind of view both
我想这样做，所以我对两者都有所了解
from language as being sort of an
从语言到 某种 程度
attempt to make a bridge between so you
试图在你之间架起一座桥梁
on the one hand there's all possible
一方面有可能
computations on the other hand there's
另一方面有计算
things we think we want to do and I view
我们认为我们想做的事情，我认为
or from language as being my best
或者语言是我最好的
attempt right now to make a way to take
现在尝试采取一种方式
our sort of human computational thinking
我们的人类计算思维
and be able to actually implement it so
并能够实际 实现它
in a sense it's a language which works
在某种意义上，它是 其工作 的语言
in two on two sides it's both a language
在两个方面，它是一种语言
where you as a as a the machine can
你作为一台机器可以在哪里
understand okay it's it's looking at
明白没关系，它正在看着
this and that's what it's going to
这就是它的目的
compute but on the other hand it's also
计算，但是， 另一方面 ， 它也
a language for us humans to think about
我们人类 思考的 一种 语言
things in computational terms so you
计算方面的事情，所以你
know if I go and I don't know one of
知道我是否去， 我不知道其中之一
these one of these things that I'm doing
我正在 做 的这些事情之一
here whatever it is that this wasn't
在这里 不管它是什么，这 是不
that exciting but but you know fine
那令人兴奋，但你知道的很好
shortest tour of the Geo position of the
最短的 地理位置 之旅
capital cities in South America that is
南美洲的首府城市
a language that's a representation in a
这是一个代表性的语言
precise language of something and the
确切的语言和东西
idea is that that's a language which we
我的想法是，这是一种 语言
humans can find useful in thinking about
人类可以在思考中找到有用的东西
things in computational terms it also
事物在计算方面也是如此
happens to be a language that the
碰巧是 一种 语言
machine can immediately understand and
机器可以立即了解和
execute and so I think this is sort of a
执行，所以我认为这 是 一种
general you know when I think about AI
一般 你知道我何时考虑 人工智能
in general the you know what is the sort
一般来说，你知道什么是那种
of what's the overall problem well part
什么是整体问题很好的部分
of the overall problem is so how do we
整体 问题是这样 我们 怎么做
tell the AI is what to do so to speak
告诉AI这是怎么回事
there's this very powerful you know this
有这个 你就知道 这 很厉害
sort of ocean of computation is what we
计算的海洋就是我们的
get to mine for purposes of building AI
为了建立 AI 而 进入我 的
kinds of things but then the question is
各种各样的事情，但接下来的 问题是
how do we tell the AI is what to do and
我们怎么告诉AI是做什么的
the what I see what I've tried to do
我所看到的是我试图做的事情
with Wolfram language is to provide a a
用Wolfram语言 来提供aa
way of kind of accessing that
访问那种方式
computation and sort of making use of
计算和利用
the knowledge that our civilization has
我们文明的知识
accumulated and because that's the you
累积，因为那就是你
know there's the general computation on
知道有一般的计算
on this side and there's the specific
在这方面，有具体的
things that we humans have thought about
我们人类想到的 事情
and the question is to make use of the
而问题是要利用
things that we've thought about to do do
我们想要做的事情
things that we care about doing actually
实际上 我们关心的 事情
if you're interested in these kinds of
如果你对这些类型感兴趣的话
things I happen to just write a blog
我碰巧写博客的事情
post where last couple of days ago it's
张贴在那里过去几天 以前， 它是
kind
类
the funny blog posts it's about some but
有趣的博客发布了一些关于一些但是
you can see the title there it came
你可以在那里看到它的标题
because a friend of miners has this
因为 矿工 的朋友 有 这个
crazy project to put little little sort
疯狂的项目放一点点
of discs or something that should
光盘或应该的东西
represent kind of the best achievements
代表一种 最好的成就
of human civilization so to speak to
人类文明可以这么说
send out it's it's hitchhiking on
发出它是搭便车的
various spacecraft that are going out
各种航天器 是走出 去
into the solar system in the next little
在接下来的小太阳系中
while and the question is what to put on
同时，问题是 穿 什么
this little disc that kind of represents
这个小圆盘就是那种 代表
you know the achievements of
你知道的 成就
civilization it's kind of it's kind of
文明它 有点像
depressing when you go back and you look
当你回去看时你会感到沮丧
at what some what people have tried to
在什么人们尝试过的
do on this before and realizing how hard
在此之前做到这一点， 并意识到 有多难
it is to tell even whether something is
它 甚至 可以告诉我 是否有事情
an artifact or not but this is this was
假象所但这是这
sort of a yeah that's a good one that's
是的，那是 一个 很好的
from 11,000 years ago can you the
从11000 年前 你可以
question is can you figure out what on
问题是你能弄清楚是 什么 吗 ？
earth it is and what it means and and
它 是什么，它 意味着 什么
this is but but so what what's relevant
这是但是，那么什么是相关的
about this is the this this whole
关于这就是这个整体
question of there are things that are
有些事情的问题
out there in the computational universe
在计算世界中
and you know when we think about
你知道当我们思考
extraterrestrial intelligence I find it
我发现了外星智慧
kind of interesting that artificial
一种有趣的 人工
intelligence is our first example of an
情报是我们的第一个 例子
alien intelligence we don't happen to
外星人的智慧我们不会发生
have found what we view as
找到了我们所看到的
extraterrestrial intelligence right now
现在是外星人的情报
but we are in the process of building
但我们在 建设的 过程
pretty decent version of an alien
相当不错 的外星人版本
intelligence here and the question is if
这里的情报和问题是，如果
you ask questions like well you know
你知道问题就好吗？
what is it thinking is it does it have a
它的 想法 是它 有一个
purpose and what it's doing and so on
目的和它正在做什么等等
and you're confronted with things like
而且你遇到过 像这样的 事情
this it's very we you can kind of do a
这就是我们你可以做的一件事
test run of you know what's what's its
试运行你知道它是什么
purpose what is it trying to do in a way
目的是 在某种程度上 尝试 做 什么
that is very similar to the kinds of
这是非常 相似的种
questions you would ask about about
你 会问 的问题 有关
extraterrestrial intelligence but in
地外情报，但在
case the the that the main point is that
案中的的主要观点 是，
I see this sort of ocean of computation
我看到了这种计算的海洋
there's the let's describe what we
让我们描述一下我们是什么
actually want to do with that ocean of
实际上想要用那个海洋
computation and that's where you know
计算，这就是你知道的地方
that's one of the primary problems we
这是我们的主要问题之一
have now people talk about you know AI
现在人们 谈论你了解AI
and what is AI going to allow us to
AI将允许 我们做什么
automate and my basic answer that would
自动化和我的 基本答案 ，将
be we'll be able to automate everything
可我们就可以 自动化 的一切
that we can describe the problem is
我们可以描述的问题是
it's not clear what we can describe or
目前还不清楚我们能描述什么或者是什么
put another way you know you imagine
用另一种你知道你想象的方式
various jobs and people are doing things
各种工作和人都在做事
they're repeated judgment jobs things
他们重复判断工作的事情
like this there where we can readily
像这样我们可以随时随地
automate those things but the thing that
自动化这些东西， 但东西
we can't really automate is saying well
我们不能真正自动化说得好
what are we trying to do that is what
我们试图做的是什么呢
are our goals because in a sense when
是 我们的目标，因为从 某种意义上说
when we see one of these systems you
当我们看到这些 系统中的一个时
know let's say let's say it's a cellular
知道让我们说它是一个 细胞
tartan here okay the question is what is
格子呢这里好的 问题是什么
this cellular automaton trying to do
这个细胞自动机试图这样做
maybe I can maybe I'll give you another
也许我可以，我会再给你一个
cellular automaton that is a little bit
细胞自动机是 一点点
more exciting here let's do this one so
更令人兴奋的是让我们这样做
that the the question is what is this
问题 是这是什么
cellular automaton trying to do you know
细胞自动机试图让你知道
it's got this whole big structure here
这里有这整个大结构
and things are happening with it we can
事情正在 发生 ，我们可以
go we can run it for a couple thousand
我们可以运行它 几千
steps we can ask it's a nice example of
我们可以问它的一个很好的例子
kind of undecidability in action what's
行动中的不确定性是什么
going to happen here this is kind of the
要在这里出现这种情况是怎么样 的
halting problem is this going to halt
停止问题就是 停止了
what's it going to do
它会怎么做
there's computational irreducibility so
这是计算不可约性
we actually can't tell this is the case
我们实际上不能说是 这种 情况
where we know this is a universal
我们知道 这是一个普遍的
computer in fact eventually well I don't
计算机其实最终 我没有
even spoil it for you if I went on long
如果我坚持下去，甚至会为你破坏它
enough it would it would go into some
足够它 会进入一些
kind of cycle but um we can ask what is
这种循环，但 我们可以问什么是
this thing trying to do what is it you
这件事试图 做 你 喜欢的事情
know is it what's it thinking about
知道它在想 什么
what's its um
什么是它的 UM
you know what's its goal what's its
你知道它的目标是什么
purpose and you know we get very quickly
目的，你知道我们得到很快
in a big mess thinking about those kinds
考虑到那些 种类， 一团糟
of things I've one of the things that
的 事情我已经的事情之一
comes out of this principle of
出来的这一原则
computational equivalence is thinking
计算等价是思考
about what kinds of things have are
关于什么样的事情是有
capable of sophisticated computation so
能够进行复杂的计算
so I mentioned a while back here sort of
所以我回到 这里提到的种类的 同时，
my personal history with Wolff malphur
我与Wolff malphur的个人历史
of having thought about doing something
具有想过做 什么
like wolf now for when I was a kid and
就像我小时候的狼一样
then believing that you sort of had to
然后相信你不得不这样 做
build a brain to make that possible and
建立一个大脑，使这成为可能
so on and one of the things that I then
等我 和其中一 件事
thought was that there was some kind of
以为是有某种
bright line between what is intelligent
什么是聪明的亮线
and what is merely computational so to
什么只是计算所以
speak in other words that there was
换句话说，有
something which is like oh we've got
像我们一样的东西
this great thing that we humans have
这是 我们人类所拥有的伟大事物
that you know as intelligence and all
你知道的是智慧和所有
these things in nature and so on and all
这些东西在自然界等等
the stuff that's going on it's just
这是 怎么回事就 可以了东西， 只是
computation or it's just you know things
计算或只是你知道的事情
operating according to rules that's
根据规则运作
different there's some bright line
不同的是有一些亮点
distinction
分别
doing these things well I think the
做好这些事我觉得
thing that came about after I'd looked
我看了 之后发生的事情
at all these cellular automata and all
在所有这些细胞自动机和所有
kinds of other things like that
其他类似的东西
is I sort of came up with this principle
我有点想出这个原则
of computational equivalence idea which
计算等价思想
we've now got quite a lot of evidence
我们现在得到了很多证据
for which I talked about people are
我谈到的 人都是
interested in but that basically there
感兴趣但基本上 就在那里
isn't a that once you reach a certain
一旦达到 某个目标 ，就不是那个
level of of computational sophistication
计算复杂程度
everything is equivalent and that means
一切都是等同的，这意味着
that that implies that there really
这意味着 确实存在
isn't a bright line distinction between
不是一条亮线之间的区别
for example the computations going on in
例如，正在进行的计算
our brains and the computations going on
我们的大脑和计算正在进行中
in these simple cellular automata and so
在这些 简单的细胞自动机中等等
on and that essentially philosophical
这基本上是哲学的
point is what actually got me to start
实际上 让我 开始了
trying to build both malphur because I
试图 建立这两个malphur因为 我
realized that gosh you know I've been
意识到天哪，你知道我去过
looking for this sort of the the magic
寻找这种 魔力
bullet of intelligence and I just
智力的 子弹 ，我只是
decided probably there isn't one and
决定可能没有一个和
actually it's all just computation and
实际上它只是计算 和
so that means we can actually
这意味着我们实际上可以
impractical
不切实际的
intelligent like thing and so that's
聪明喜欢的东西，所以那就是
what I think is the case is that there
我认为的情况 是那里
really isn't sort of a bright line
真的不是那种 一条亮 线
distinction and that has that has more
区别与 已具有更多
extreme consequences like people will
像人们一样的极端后果
say things like you know the weather has
说你知道天气这样的事情
a mind of its own okay
一个自己的想法没关系
sounds kind of silly sounds kind of
听起来有点傻傻的声音
animistic primitive and so on but in
万物有灵的原始等等但是在
fact the you know fluid dynamics of the
事实上，你知道的流体动力学
weather is as computationally
天气和计算一样
sophisticated as the stuff that goes on
作为持续的东西是复杂的
in our brains but we can start asking
在 我们的大脑中， 但我们可以开始 询问
but then you say but the weather doesn't
但是你说，但天气没有
have a purpose you know what's the
有目的你 知道是什么
purpose of the weather well you know
那么你知道天气 的目的
maybe the weather is trying to equalize
也许天气正试图平衡
the temperature between the you know the
你知道之间的温度
the North Pole and the tropics or
北极和热带 或
something and then we have to say well
什么，然后我们必须说好
but that's not a purpose in the way that
但这不是 一个目的
we think about purposes that's just you
我们考虑的目的就是你
know and we get very confused and in the
知道，我们变得非常困惑，并在
end what we realize is when we're
结束我们所知道的是什么时候
talking about things like purposes we
谈论我们的目的
have to have this kind of chain of
必须有这种链
provenance that goes back to humans and
可以追溯到人类 和 人类的起源
human history and all that kind of thing
人类的历史和所有这些 事情
and I think it's the same type of thing
我认为这是同类型 的事情
when we talk about computation and AI
当我们谈论计算和人工智能时
and so on the thing that we this
等我们这件事
question of sort of purpose goals things
某种目的事物的问题
like this that's a thing which is
像这样， 这是一件事
intrinsically human and not something
本质上是人类而不是某种东西
that we can ever sort of automatically
我们可以 永远排序自动
generate it makes no sense to talk about
产生这是没有意义的谈论
automatically generating it
自动生成它
because these computational systems they
因为这些计算系统他们
do all kinds of stuff you know we can
做你知道我们能做的各种 事情
say they've got a purpose we can
说他们已经有了一个目的，我们可以
attribute purposes to them etcetera
属于他们的目的等等
etcetera etcetera
等等
but you know ultimately it's sort of the
但你最终知道它的类型
human thread of purpose that we have to
我们必须要有的 人性 线索
have to deal with so that means for
必须处理所以这意味着
example when we talk about AIS and we
我们谈论 AIS和 我们的例子
were interested in things like so how do
对这样的事情感兴趣怎么做
we tell you know like like we'd like to
我们告诉你，就像我们想要的那样
be able to tell we talk about AI ethics
能够告诉我们谈论人工智能道德
for example we'd like to be able to make
例如，我们希望能够做到
a statement to the AIS like you know
像你知道的那样向AIS发表声明
please be nice to us humans um and
请善待我们人类 UM和
that's a you know that's something so
这就是你知道 的事情
one of the issues there is so talking
的问题之一， 有 这么说话
about that kind of thing one of the
关于那种 的一 件事
issues is how are we going to make a
问题是我们将如何制作一个
statement like be nice to us humans
声明对我们人类很好
what's the you know in how are we going
你知道我们怎么回事
to explain that to an AI and this is
向 AI 解释， 这是
where again you know my my efforts to
你再次知道我的努力
build a language a computational
建立一种计算语言
communication language that bridges the
桥接 通信语言
world of what we humans think about and
什么我们人类思考世界 ，
the world of what is possible in
可能的世界
computation is important and so one of
计算很重要，所以其中之一
things I've been interested in is
我一直感兴趣的是
actually building what I call a symbolic
实际建立我称之为象征性的东西
discourse language that can be a general
话语可以是一般的
representation for sort of the kinds of
代表各种各样的
things that we might want to put in that
的事情，我们 可能要 摆在那
we might want to to say and things like
我们可能要到说之 类 的东西
be nice to him and so sort of a little
要对他好等等之类 的一点点
bit background to that so you know in
有点 背景 ，所以你知道
the modern world people are keen on
现代世界的人们都热衷于此
smart contracts they often think of them
他们经常想到 的智能合约
as being deeply tied into blockchain
与区块链紧密联系在一起
which I don't think is really quite
我不 认为这是 非常的
right
对
the important thing about smart
关于聪明的重要事情
contracts is it's a way of having sort
合同是一种排序方式
of an agreement between parties which
各方之间的协议
can be executed automatically and that
可以自动地， 并且执行
agreement may be you know you may choose
协议可能是您知道您可以选择的
to sort of anchor that agreement in a
以某种方式锚定该 协议
blockchain you may not but the whole
区块链你可能不是整个
point is you have to what you you know
重点是你必须 知道你 所知道的
when people write legal contracts they
当人们写法律合同时
write them in an approximation to
他们写在近似
English they write them in legalese
英语他们用法律术语写它们
typically because they're trying to
通常是因为他们正在努力
write them in something a little bit
他们写的东西一点点
more precise than regular English but
比普通英语更精确但是
the limiting case of that is to make a
的是 ，极限情况是使
symbolic discourse language in which you
你在其中的象征性话语
can write the contract and code
可以写合同和代码
basically and the the I've been very
基本上和我一直很
interested in using wolfmann language to
有兴趣 使用wolfmann语言
do that because in wolfen language we
这样做是因为在 沃尔芬语中我们
have a language which Candice
有一种语言，Candice
bribe things about the world and we can
贿赂关于世界的事情 ，我们可以
talk about the kinds of things that
谈论各种各样 的 事情，
people actually talk about in contracts
人们 实际上在合同中谈论
and so on and we're most of the way
等等，我们一路走来
there to being able to do that and then
有没有能够做到这一点，然后
when you start thinking about that you
当你开始考虑 你的时候
start thinking about okay so we've got
开始思考 好了 ，所以我们有
this language to describe things that we
用这种语言描述 我们的 事情
that we care about in the world and so
我们关心 的是世界等等
when it comes to things like tell the
说到这样的事情
AIS to be nice to the humans we can
AIS对我们的人类很好
imagine using often language to sort of
想象经常使用 的语言来进行排序 的
build an AI Constitution that says this
建立一个说 这个 的AI宪法
is how the AI supposed to work but when
在 AI应该如何工作的，但是 当
we talk about sort of just the the
我们谈论 的 那种只是在
untethered you know the untethered AI
不受束缚你知道不受束缚的AI
doesn't have any particular it's just
没有任何特别的东西
going to do what it does and if we want
要 做到它做什么，如果我们想
it to you know if we want to somehow
如果我们想 以某种方式 告诉你
align it with human purposes we have to
与我们人类的目的对齐
have some way to sort of talk to the AI
有一些方式 可以与AI 进行对话
and that's that's a you know I view my
这就是你知道我看到我的
efforts to build or from language as as
建立或从语言的努力
a way to do that I mean I you know as I
一种方法，我的意思是我，你知道我
was showing at the beginning you can use
在开始时你可以 使用
you can take natural language and with
你可以采取自然语言和
natural language you can build up a
你可以建立自然语言
certain amount of you can say a certain
一定数量的你可以说一定
number of things in natural language you
你用自然语言的东西数量
can then say well how do we make this
然后可以说好我们如何做到这一点
more precise in a precise symbolic
精确的象征性更精确
language if you want to build up more
语言， 如果你想积累更多
complicated things it gets hard to do
复杂的事情很难做到
that in natural language and so you have
用 自然语言，所以你有
to kind of build up more serious
有点建立更严重
programs in in in symbolic language and
在节目中的符号语言和
I've probably been numb been yakking a
我可能已经麻木 了
while here
在这里
and I'm happy to I can talk about all
我很高兴 我可以谈论所有
kinds of different things here but that
这里有 各种不同的东西 ，但那
maybe I've not seen as many reactions as
也许我没见过那么多的反应
I might have expected to think so I I'm
我本可以期待这样 想，我是
not sure which things people are
不确定 人是谁
interested in which they're not but so
感兴趣的是他们不是这样
maybe I should maybe I should stop here
也许我应该在这里停下来
and we can have discussion questions
我们可以有讨论问题
comments yes
评论是的
[Applause]
[掌声]
if two microphones if you have questions
如果有 两个麦克风，如果你 有问题
please come out so I have a quick
请出来所以我快点
question it's goes to the earlier part
问题是前面的部分
of your talk where you say you don't
你 说话，你说你没有 的
build a top-down ontology you actually
你实际上构建了一个自上而下的本体论
build from the bottom up but disparate
从下往上构建但不同
domains what do you feel are the core
域名你觉得什么是 核心
technologies of the knowledge
知识技术
representation which you use within
您在其中使用的表示
Wolfram Alpha that allows you you know
Wolfram Alpha 让你知道
different domains to reason about each
关于每一个的不同领域
other to come up with solutions and is
其他提出解决方案 ，是
there any feeling of differentiability
有任何差异感
for examples if you were to come up with
为例子，如果你要拿出
a plan to do something new within
计划在其中做一些 新 事物
Wolfram Alpha language you know how
Wolfram Alpha语言你知道怎么做
would you go about doing that me okay so
你能不能这样做 我还好吧
we've done maybe a couple of thousand
我们已经做了几千个
domains okay the what is actually
域名确实是实际的
involved in doing one of these domains
参与做 这些 领域 之一
it's it's a gnarly business every domain
这是每个领域都是一项愚蠢的业务
has some crazy different thing about it
有关于它的一些疯狂的事情不同
I tried to make up actually a while ago
我实际上是在不久前尝试过
we um let me show you something a kind
我们嗯让 我告诉你一些事情 的一种
of a hierarchy of what it means to make
它意味着什么 的层次结构
um see if I can find this here kind of a
嗯，看看我能在这里发现这种情况
hierarchy of what it means to make a
意味着什么 ，使层次
domain computable where is it that's
域可计算在哪里它是
okay here we go so there's sort of a
还好在这里我们去 所以有排序 的
hierarchy of levels of what it means to
意味着什么程度的层次结构
make a domain computable from just you
使域可以计算出来
know you've got some you know you've got
知道你有一些你知道你有的
some array of data that's quite
一些数据非常相似
structured forget you know the separate
结构化忘了你知道单独的
issue about extracting things from
从中提取东西的问题
unstructured data but let's imagine that
非结构化数据，但让我们想象一下
you were given you know a a bunch of
你被告知了一堆
data about landing sites of meteorites
关于陨石着陆点的数据
or something okay so you go through
或者别的什么， 所以你经历
various levels so you know things like
各种 级别， 所以 你知道的事情
okay the landing sites the meteorites
好的，陨石的着陆点
are the are the positions just strings
是 字符串的位置
or they some kind of canonical
或者他们某种规范
representation of geo position is the
地理位置的 表示 是
you know is the type of meteorite you
你知道 陨石 的类型 吗？
know some of them are iron meteorites
知道有些人 是 铁陨石
some of them are stone meteorites have
其中一些是石陨石
you made a canonical representation have
你做了一个规范的代表
you made some kind of way to to identify
你做了某种方式来识别
what some sorry go ahead no no I mean to
什么有些抱歉继续前进 不是我的意思
do that so my question is like you know
那样做我的问题就像你知道的那样
if you did have positions as a string as
如果你确实有一个字符串的位置
well as a canonical representation do
还有一个典型代表做
you have redundant
你有多余的
pieces of the same redundant
同样多余的碎片
representations of the same information
表示相同的信息
in the different no I mean I'll go you
在不同的不，我的意思是我会去你
always everything canonical that you
总是一切都是规范你的
have yeah I have a minimal
是的，我有 一个最小的
representation of everything yeah our
代表一切都是我们的
goal is to make everything canonical now
目标是让一切都成为现实
that's you know there is a lot of
这是你知道有很多 的
complexity in doing that I mean if you
在 这样做，我的意思是，如果你的复杂性
you know in each okay so another feature
你知道每个还好，所以另一个功能
of these domains
这些 域名
okay so there's another another thing to
好了，还有另一个另一回事
say um you know it will be lovely if one
说你嗯，你知道 如果一个人 会 很 可爱
could just automate everything and cut
可以自动化 一切并削减
the humans out of the loop
人类走出了循环
turns out this doesn't work and in fact
原来，这并不工作，实际上
whenever we do these domains it's fairly
每当我们做这些域名时， 它都是公平的
critical to have expert humans who
拥有专家的人是至关重要的
really understand the domain or you
真的了解域名还是 你
simply get it wrong and it's also having
只是弄错了，它也有
said that once you've done enough
说你做完了就够了
domains you can do a lot of cross
域名你可以做很多 交叉
checking between domains and we are the
检查域之间我们是
number one reporters of error and of
第一名 记者的错误和
errors and in pretty much all
错误，几乎所有
standardized data sources because we can
标准化数据源，因为我们可以
do that kind of cross checking but I
做这种交叉检查，但我 的
think you know if you ask the question
如果你问这个问题，请认为你知道
what's involved in in bringing online a
在线提供什么参与
new domain it's you know those sort of
新域名，你知道 那些
hierarchy of things you know some of
事情层级你知道一些 的
those take a few hours you can get to
那些需要几个小时才能 到达
the point of of having you know we've
让你知道我们的意义
got good enough tools for ingesting data
有足够的工具来摄取数据
figuring out oh those are names of
弄清楚那些是谁的名字
cities in that column let's you know
那个栏目中的 城市 让你知道
that's canonicalized those you know some
那是规范化你认识的人
may be questions but many of them will
可能是问题，但其中许多人会
be able to to nail down and to get to
能够钉牢并到达
the full level of you've got some
你有一些完整的水平
complicated domain and it's fully
复杂的领域 ，它是完全的
computable is probably a year of work
可计算可能 是一年的工作
and and you might say well gosh why are
并且你可能会说天哪，为什么
you wasting you their time you've got to
你浪费了他们的时间
be able to automate that so you can
能够 自动化，所以你可以
probably tell we're fairly sophisticated
可能告诉我们相当复杂
about machine learning kinds of things
关于机器学习的东西
and so on and we have tried you know to
等等 ，我们已经尝试过你知道了
automate as much as we can and we have
自动化的多， 我们 可以，我们 有
got a pretty efficient pipeline but if
有一个非常有效的管道，但如果
you actually want to get it right and
你真的想要 把它弄好
you see it is an example of what what
你看它是什么的一个例子
happens that there's a level even going
碰巧有一个水平 甚至去
between wolf now for more from language
狼之间现在 更多来自 语言
there's a level of so for example let's
有一个水平，例如让我们
say you're looking at you know lakes in
说你看着你知道 湖泊
Wisconsin okay so people are querying
威斯康星州好，所以人们都在 询问
about lakes in Wisconsin and
关于威斯康星州和加拿大的湖泊
WolframAlpha they'll name a particular
WolframAlpha他们会说出一个特别的名字
lake and they want to know you know how
湖，他们想 知道你怎么知道
big is the lake
大湖是
okay fine in Wolfram language they'll be
好吧，他们会用Wolfram语言
doing a systematic computation about
做一个系统的计算
lakes in Wisconsin so if there's a lake
威斯康星州的湖泊，如果有一个湖泊
missing you're gonna get the wrong
想念你会错的
answer and so that's a kind of higher
答案，这是一种 更高的
level of difficulty okay but the this
困难程度 还可以，但这个
yeah I think you're asking some more
是的，我想你还要问一些
technical questions about ontologies and
关于本体和技术的技术问题
I can try and answer those actually one
我可以尝试回答那些实际问题
quick question and you know that's
快速的问题，你知道 的
there's a lot of other questions yes
还有很多其他问题
that's right okay all right very much my
这是正确的没关系没关系 很我
cyclist as to the left here I got a
骑自行车作为 向左这里我得到了
simple question who or what are your key
简单的问题你的关键是 谁 或什么
influences oh gosh in terms of language
在语言方面影响天哪
design for from language are in the
来自语言的设计在
context of machine intelligence if you
机器智能的背景，如果你
like if you want to make it tighter to
就像你想让它 更紧密
this audience I don't know I've been
这个观众我不知道我去过
absorbing stuff forever I think my main
永远吸收的东西我 认为我的主要
in terms of language design probably
在语言设计方面可能
list span APL were my sort of early
列表范围APL是我 的早期
influences but in terms of thinking
影响，但在思考方面
about AI hmm you know in I mean I'm kind
关于AI嗯，你知道我的意思是我很善良
of quite knowledgeable I like history of
相当懂行，我喜欢历史
science so I'm pretty knowledgeable
科学让我知识渊博
about the the early history of kind of
关于早期 的 那种 历史
mathematical logic symbolic kinds of
数学逻辑象征性的
things I would say okay maybe I can
事情我会说好吧 也许我可以
answer that in the negative okay I have
回答 是 否定的好吧， 我有
for example in building Wolfram Alpha I
例如，建立Wolfram Alpha I
thought gosh let me do my homework let
以为天哪让我做功课了
me learn all about computational
我学习所有关于计算的知识
linguistics let me hire some
语言学让我雇用一些
computational linguistics PhDs that will
计算语言学博士将会
be a good way to get this started
这是一个很好的方式来开始
turns out we used almost nothing from
结果我们几乎没用过任何东西
the from the previous sort of history of
在从以前的那种历史
computational linguistics partly because
计算 语言学 部分是因为
what we were trying to do namely short
我们试图做的就是简短
question natural language understanding
质疑自然语言的理解
is different from a lot of the national
从很多国家的不同
language processing which has been was
语言处理一直是
done in the past I also have made to my
在过去做过我也做过我的
disappointment very little use of you
失望很少使用 你
know people like Marvin Minsky for
知道像马文明斯基这样的人
example I really don't think I mean I
例子我真的不 认为我的意思是 我
knew Marvin for years and in fact some
马尔文已经多年了， 事实上已经知道了
of his early work on simple Turing
他早期关于简单图灵的工作
machines and things those are probably
机器和那些可能的东西
more influential to me than his work on
对我的影响比他的工作更有影响力
on AI and you know probably
关于AI，你可能知道
I my mistake of not understanding that
我错误地认识到这一点
better but really I would say that I'd
更好，但我真的想说 ， 我会
been been rather uninfluenced by by sort
一直没有受到影响
of the traditional AI kinds of things I
我 传统的 AI种类的东西
mean it probably hasn't helped that I've
意味着它 可能没有帮助 ，我已经
kind of lived through a time when when
那种活过的时候
sort of AI went from you know when I was
AI排序从你去知道当我是
a kid a I was gonna solve everything in
一个孩子，我 会解决 一切
the world and then you know it kind of
世界， 那么 你就知道它种
decayed for a while and then sort of
腐烂了一段时间， 然后一点点
come back so I so I would say that I can
回来 ，所以我，所以我要说的 是 ， 我可以
describe my negative my non influences
描述我的负面影响
better than my impression you gave is
比我的印象更好，你给的
that you made your own head and it
你创造了自己的头脑和它
sounds as though that's pretty much
听起来好像那是 相当多
right yeah I mean yes I I mean insofar
对，是的，我的意思是，是的，我的意思是
as those things to me I mean look things
对我来说，这些东西我的意思是看东西
like the you know okay so for example
就像你知道的那样好吧
studying simple programs as and trying
学习简单的程序和尝试
to understand the universe of simple
了解宇宙的简单
programs actually the personal history
程序实际上是个人历史
of that sort of interesting I mean I you
那种 有趣的我的意思是 你
know I used to do particle physics when
知道我 曾经做过粒子物理学
I was a kid basically and then I
我基本上还是个孩子，然后是我
actually got interested okay so I'll
实际上有兴趣好吧所以我会
totally the history of that just as an
完全是那个历史
example of how sort of interesting is a
例如某种 有趣的是 怎样 一个
sort of history of ideas type thing so I
有点想法的历史类型的东西所以我
was interested in in how order arises in
对订单如何产生感兴趣
the universe so you know you start off
宇宙， 所以你知道你开始
from the hot Big Bang and then pretty
从 热的大爆炸然后漂亮
soon you end up with a bunch of humans
很快你就会结束一堆人类
and galaxies and things like this how
和星系这样的事情如何
does this happen so I got on just in
这是否发生，所以我继续前进
that question I was also interested in
这个问题 我 也很感兴趣
in things like knowing that works for
在知道如何工作的事情
sort of AI purposes and I thought let me
有点人工智能的目的，我想让我
make a minimal model that encompasses
制作一个包含的最小模型
sort of how complex things arise from
一种复杂的事物是如何产生的
from other stuff and I ended up sort of
从其他东西， 我最终有点
making simpler and simpler and simpler
使更简单，更简单， 更简单
models and eventually wound up with
模特们最终结束了
cellular automata and which I didn't
细胞自动机，我没有
know were called cellular automata when
知道被称为细胞自动机的时候
I started looking at them and then found
我开始看着他们然后找到了
they didn't interesting things and the
他们 没有 有趣的东西和
two areas were cellular automata had
两个方面是元胞自动机 有
been singularly unuseful in analyzing
在分析方面一点都没有用
things our large-scale structure in the
事物我们的大规模 结构
universe and neural networks so turned
宇宙和神经网络如此转变
out but but that by the way the fact
了，但不过 是顺便把事实
that I kind of even imagined that one
我甚至想到了那一个
could just start yeah I should say you
可能只是开始是的我应该说你
know I've been doing physics and in
我知道我一直 在 做物理学
physics the kind of intellectual concept
物理学的那种智力概念
is you take the world as it is and you
你是把它带走了世界吗？
try and drill down and find out what you
尝试和深入 ，并找出 你
know what makes the world out of
知道是什么让这个世界脱颖而出
primitives and so on it's
原始等等
you know reduce to find things then I
你知道减少找东西然后我
built my first computer language a thing
建立我的第一个计算机 语言的东西
called SMP which went the other way
称SMP是另一种方式
around where I was just like I'm just
在我 身边的 地方 就像我一样
gonna make up this computer language and
要编写这种计算机语言和
you know just make up what I want the
你知道只是弥补我想要的东西
primitives to be and I'm gonna build
原始人和我 要 建立
stuff up from it I think that the fact
我认为这是事实
that I kind of had the idea of doing
我有点想做 的 事情
things like making up cellular automata
像制作细胞自动机的东西
as possible models for the world was a
作为世界的可能模型是 一个
consequence of the fact that I worked on
的 事实后果是我的工作
this computer language which was a thing
这种计算机语言是 一件事
which worked the opposite way around
围绕工作相反的方式
from the way that one is used to doing
从一个习惯做的方式
natural science which is sort of this
自然科学 是 有点这个
reductionist approach and that's I mean
简化方法，这是我的意思
so that's just an example of it you know
所以这只是 你知道的 一个 例子
I found I happen to have spent a bunch
我发现我碰巧花了很多钱
of time studying as I say history of
时间研究， 因为我说的 历史
science and one of my one of my hobbies
科学和我的一个爱好
is sort of history of ideas I even wrote
有点像 我写 的 想法 的 历史
this little book called idea makers
这本小书名为创意制作者
which is about biographies of a bunch of
这是关于一堆的传记
people who for one reason or another
出于某种原因的人
I've written about and so I'm I'm always
我写过，所以我总是这样
curious about this thing about how do
关于这件事怎么做好奇
people actually wind up figuring out the
人们实际上 最终搞清楚了
things they figure out and you know one
他们想出的东西，你知道一个
of the one of the conclusions of my you
我的你 的结论 之一
know investigations of many people is
知道很多人的调查是
there are very rarely moments of
很少有时刻
inspiration usually it's long
灵感通常很长
multi-decade kinds of things which only
只有十年的种类
later get compressed into something
后来压缩成了某种东西
short and also the path is often much
简短而且路径往往很多
you know it's it's it's quite what can I
你知道这是它很 我能
say
说
that the steps are quite small and you
你的步骤很小
know but the path is often kind of
知道，但路径往往是那种
complicated and that's what that's what
很复杂， 那是什么
it's been for me so I simple question
对 我来说这是一个简单的 问题
complex answer sorry so when I basically
复杂的答案很抱歉 所以当我基本上
see from the Wolfram languages it's a
从Wolfram 语言看， 它是一个
way to describe all of objective reality
描述所有客观现实的方式
it's kind of formalizing just about the
这种形式正式化了
entire domain of discourse use a
整个话语领域都使用了
philosophical term and you kind of
哲学术语和你有点
hinted at this in your lecture where
在你的演讲中暗示了这一点
that where it sort of leaves office is
离开办公室的地方是
that when we start to talk about more
当我们开始谈论 更多时
esoteric philosophical concepts purpose
深奥的哲学概念目的
I guess this would lean into things like
我想这会倾向于像
epistemology because essentially you
认识论，因为基本上你
only have science there and as amazing
只有那里的科学和惊人的
as Sciences there are other things that
作为科学还有其他的东西
are talked about not you know you know
谈到 你不知道你知道
like idealism versus materialism etc do
像理想主义与唯物主义等一样
you have an idea of how Wolfram might or
你知道Wolfram可能是怎么样的
might not be able to branch into those
可能无法分支到 那些
discourses because I'm
话语，因为我
hearing echoes in my head at that time
那个 时候听到了我脑中的回声
bostrm said that nai needs a you know
boström说 nai需要你知道
when you give an AI a purpose there's
当你给AI一个目的时
like I think he said philosophers are
就像我认为 他说的 哲学家一样
divided completely evenly between the
在两者之间完全分开
top four ways to measure how good
衡量有多好的 四种方法
something should be it's like
应该是这样的东西
utilitarianism and sure brother for most
功利主义和最肯定的兄弟
Japanese yeah so the first thing is I
日本是的，所以第一 件事就是我
mean this problem of making what okay
意味着 做出什么 好的 问题
about 300 years ago people like light
大约300年前 人们喜欢 光
knits we're interested in the same
针织 我们 对此感兴趣
problem that I'm interested in which is
我感兴趣的问题是哪个
how do you formalize sort of everyday
你如何形象化每天
discourse and Leibniz had the original
话语和 莱布尼兹 有原创
idea you know he was originally trained
你知道他最初受过训练的想法
as a lawyer and he had this idea if he
作为一名律师，他有这个想法
could only reduce all law all legal
只能减少所有合法的法律
questions to matters of logic he could
他可以提出逻辑问题
have a machine that would basically
有一台机器基本上
describe every you know answer every
每一个都描述你所知道的每一个
legal case right he was unfortunately a
法律案件权利他很遗憾
few hundred years too early even though
尽管 过了几百年 太早了
he did have you know he tried to he
他确实让你 知道他试过了他
tried to do all kinds of things very
我试图做各种各样的事情
similar things I've tried to do like he
类似我试图做的事情就像他一样
tried to get various Dukes to assemble
试图让各种公爵组装
big libraries of data and stuff like
大数据库和类似的东西
this but but the point so what he tried
但是这一点，所以他尝试了
to do was to make a formalized
要做的是正式化
representation of everyday discourse for
日常话语的表现形式
whatever reason for the last 300 years
无论过去300年的原因是什么
basically people haven't tried to do
基本上人们都没有尝试过
that there's it's a almost completely
这几乎是完全的
barren landscape there was this period
贫瘠的景观就在这个时期
of time in the 1600s when people talked
人们谈论 的时间 是在17世纪
about philosophical languages Leibniz
关于哲学语言Leibniz
was why and a guy called John Wilkins
是为什么和一个叫John Wilkins的人
was another and they tried to you know
是另一个，他们试图让你知道
break down human thought into something
把人类思想分解成某种东西
symbolic people haven't done that for a
象征性的人没有做到这一点
long time in terms of what can we do
在 我们能做什么 方面很长一段时间
that with you know I've been trying to
你知道我一直在努力
figure out what the best way to do it is
弄清楚最好的方法是什么
I think it's actually not as hard as one
我认为它实际上并不像一个那么难
might think these areas one thing you
可能会认为这些领域是你的一件事
have to understand these areas like
必须了解这些领域
philosophy and so on are they're on the
哲学等等 他们是谁
harder end I mean things like a good
更难结束我的意思是好事
example typical example you know I want
你知道我想要的典型例子
to have a piece of chocolate okay they
有一块 巧克力 他们 没关系
in morphing language right now we have a
在变形语言 现在我们有一个
pretty good description of pieces of
很好的描述件
chocolate we know all sorts of you know
巧克力我们知道各种你 知道的
we probably know 100 different kinds of
我们可能知道 100种不同的
chocolate we know how big the pieces are
我们知道巧克力有多大
all that kind of thing the I want part
所有 我想要 的东西
of that sentence we can't do that right
那句话我们做不到这一点
now but I don't think that's that hard
现在， 但我不认为这很难
and I'm you know that's now if you ask
如果你问，我现在就知道了
let's say we had I think the different
让我们说我认为不同
thing you're saying is let's say we had
你说的是让我们说我们有
the omnipotent AI so to speak that was
无所不能的AI可以这么说
able to you know where we turn over the
能够 为您知道我们改过 的
control of the central bank to the AI we
控制中央银行对 AI我们
turn over all these other things to the
把所有这些事情都交给 了
AI then the question is we say to the AI
我们问的是人工智能问题
now do the right thing and then the
现在做 正确的事情然后
problem with that is and this is why I
问题就是这就是为什么我
talk about you know creating AI
说说 你知道 创建AI
constitutions and so on we have
我们有宪法等等
absolutely no idea what do the right
绝对不知道什么是正确的
thing is supposed to mean and
事情应该意味着和
philosophers have been arguing about
哲学家们一直争论
that you know utilitarianism is an
你知道功利主义是一种
example of that of one of the answers to
例如 ， 该答案之一
that although it's not a complete answer
虽然这不是 一个完整的答案
by any means it's not not really an
以任何方式它不是不是一个真正的
answer it's just a way of posing the
回答它只是一种 摆出姿势的方式
question and so I think that the you
问题所以我认为你
know one of one of the features of so I
我知道其中一个 特征之一
think it's a really hard problem to you
认为这 对你来说 真的 很难
know you think to yourself what should
知道你认为 自己应该做些什么
the AI Constitution actually say so
AI宪法实际上是这样说的
first thing you might think is oh
你可能会想到的第一件事就是哦
there's going to be you know something
你会知道一些事情
like Asimov's laws of robotics there's
像机器人阿西莫夫的法律 有
going to be one you know golden rule for
将成为一个你知道黄金法则的人
a eyes and if we just follow that golden
一只眼睛，如果我们只是跟随那金色
rule all well okay I think that that is
排除一切 安好 好吧 ，我认为这是
absolutely impossible and in fact I
绝对不可能 ，事实上我
think you can even sort of
想你甚至可以 排序的
mathematically prove that that's
从数学上证明了这一点
impossible because I think as soon as
不可能的，因为我只要想
you have a system that you know
你有 ， 你知道 一个系统
essentially what you're trying to do is
基本上就是 你正在试图做的是
you're trying to put in constraints that
你试图 把在约束
okay basically as soon as you have a
好吧， 基本上 你有一个
system that shows computational
显示计算的系统
irreducibility I think it is inevitable
不可减少我认为这是 不可避免的
that you have ace of have unintended
你 有无意识的王牌
consequences of things which means that
事情的后果，这意味着
you never get to just say put everything
你永远不会只是说把一切
in this one very nice box you always
你 总是在这个非常漂亮的盒子里
have to say let's put in a patch here
不得不说让我们在这里补丁
let's put in a patch there and so on a
让我们把一个补丁有等一
version of this much more abstract
这个版本更加抽象
version of this of girdles theorem so
这个腰带定理的版本如此
girdles theorem is you know it starts up
束带定理你知道它启动了
by taking the you know it's girls
通过带你知道 它的女孩
theorem is trying to talk about integers
定理试图谈论整数
it says start off with piano's axioms
它说从钢琴的公理开始
turner's axioms you might say in piano
你可能会用钢琴说的 特纳的公理
thought describe the integers and
思想描述整数和
nothing but the integers okay so
不过整数好 了，
anything that's provable from pianos
任何可以从 钢琴中 证明的东西
axioms will be true about integers and
公理和 整数都是正确的
vice-versa okay
反之亦然
what girls theorem shows is that you can
女孩定理显示的是你可以
that will never work that there are an
永远不会工作 ， 有 一个
infinite
无穷
hierarchy of patches that you have to
你必须要有的补丁层次结构
put on two pianos axioms if you want to
如果你愿意的话，戴上两个钢琴公理
describe the integers and nothing about
描述整数而不是什么
the integers and I think the same is
整数，我 认为同样如此
true if you want to have a legal system
如果你想拥有一个法律 系统 ，那就是真的
effectively that has no bizarre
实际上没有奇怪的
unintended consequences so I don't think
意想不到的后果所以我不这么认为
it's possible to just say you know if
你可以说你知道是否
you when you're describing something in
当你在描述某些东西的时候
the world that's complicated like I
像我 这样 复杂的世界
don't think it's possible to just have a
不要认为有可能 只有一个
small set of rules that will always do
总是会做的一小套规则
what we want so to speak I think it's
我们想要说什么我想是的
inevitable that you have to have a long
不可避免的，你必须有一个长期
essentially code of laws and that's what
基本上是法律的代码，那是什么
you know so my guess is that what will
你知道，所以我的猜测是 ， 会 出现什么
actually have to happen is you know as
实际上 必须 发生的 是你知道的
we try and describe what you want the
我们试着 描述你想要的东西
eyes to do you know I don't know the
眼睛， 你知道我不知道
socio-political aspects of how we'll
我们如何做的社会政治方面
figure out whether it's 1 AI
弄清楚它是否是 1 AI
Constitution or 1 per you know city or
宪法或 1你 知道 城市或
whatever we can talk about that that's a
无论我们谈论什么都是一个
separate issue but but um you know I
单独的问题，但你知道 我
think what will happen is it'll be much
想想会发生什么事情 会 很多
like human laws it'll be a complicated
像人类法则一样复杂
thing that gets progressively patched
逐渐修补的 东西
and so I think it's it's some and these
所以我认为这是一些和这些
ideas like you know oh we'll just make
你知道的 想法 哦，我们只会做
the eyes you know run the world
你认识的眼睛管理世界
according to you know Mills you know
根据你知道 米尔斯你知道
John Stuart Mill's idea it's not gonna
约翰斯图亚特米尔的想法不会
work which is not surprising this
工作这并不奇怪 ， 这
philosophy has has has made the point
哲学已经说明了 这 一点
that it's not as easy it's not an easy
它并不容易，这并不容易
problem for the last two thousand years
过去两千年的问题
and they're right it's not an easy
他们是对的并不容易
problem thank you yeah I you're talking
问题谢谢你，我说你在说话
about computational irreducibility and
关于计算不可约性和
computational equivalents and also that
计算等价物也是如此
earlier on in your intellectual
早些时候你的知识分子
adventures you're interested in particle
冒险你对粒子感兴趣
physics and things like that I've heard
物理学 和 我听过的 事情
you make the comment before in other
你之前在其他地方发表评论
contexts that things like molecules
像分子这样的东西
compute and I was just ask you exactly
计算和我 只是问你到底
you you know what you mean by that in
你，你知道你在什么意思
what sense does a molecule I mean what
分子是什么意思我的意思是什么
would you like to compute so to speak I
你想算我的计算吗？
mean in other words you what what is the
换句话说，你的意思是什么
case is that you know one definition of
案例是 你知道 一个定义
you're computing is given a particular
你的计算是特定的
computation like I don't know finding
计算就像我不知道发现
square roots or something you know you
平方根或某事，你知道你
can program a you know
可以编程 你 知道
the surprising thing is that an awful
令人惊讶的是，这太糟糕了
lot of stuff can be programmed to do any
很多东西 都 可以 编程 来做任何事情
computation you want that's some and you
计算你想要的是一些和你
know when it comes to I mean I think for
知道什么时候我的意思是我想
example when you look at nanotechnology
例如，当你看纳米技术
and so on the the current you know one
等你当前知道的那个
of the current beliefs says to make very
当前的信念说得非常好
small computers you should take what we
小型电脑你应该拿走我们的东西
know about making big computers and just
知道如何制作大型计算机
you know make them smaller so to speak I
你知道 让它们变小 我可以这么说
don't think that's the approach you have
不要以为这就是你的方法
to use I think you can take the
使用我认为你可以采取
components that exist at the level of
存在 于级别的组件
molecules and say how do we assemble
分子并说我们如何组装
those components to be able to do
那些组件能够做到
complicated computations I mean it's
复杂的计算我的意思是
like the cellular automata that the you
就像你的细胞自动机一样
know the underlying rule for the
知道的基本规则
cellular automaton is very simple yet
细胞自动机非常简单
when that rule is applied many times it
当该规则 多次 应用 时
can do a sophisticated computation so I
我可以做一个复杂的计算
think that that's the that's the sense
认为这就是感觉
in which what can I say the raw material
其中我能说什么 原料
that you need for computation can be you
你需要 计算可以是 你
know there's a great diversity in the
知道有很大的差异 在
raw material that you can use for
您可以使用的原材料
computation our particular human
计算我们特定的人类
development you know stack of of
开发你知道堆栈的
technologies that we use for computation
我们 用于计算的技术
right now is just one particular path
现在只是一条特定的道路
and we can you know so a very practical
我们你能知道这非常实用吗？
example of this is algorithmic drugs so
这方面的例子就是算法药物
the question is right now drugs pretty
问题是现在药物很漂亮
much work by most drugs work well you
大多数药物的大量工作对你有用
know there is a binding site and a
知道有一个绑定站点和一个
molecule drug fits into binding site
分子药物适合 结合位点
does something question is can you
你 能做些什么问题
imagine having something where the
想象有什么东西在哪里
molecule you know is something which has
你知道的分子是有的东西
computations going on in it where it
在它里面进行的计算
goes around and it looks at that you
善有善报， 它 看起来在你
know that thing it's supposed to be
知道那 应该 是的东西
binding to and it figures out oh there's
绑定到它并且它计算 出哦
this knob here and that knob there it
这里的旋钮和旋钮在那里
reconfigures itself it's computing
重新配置自己的计算
something it's trying to figure out you
它试图找出你的东西
know is this likely to be a tumor cell
知道这可能是一个肿瘤细胞
or whatever based on some more
或者基于更多的东西
complicated thing that's the type of
复杂的东西是那种类型
thing that I mean by by computations
通过计算我的意思
happening at an R color scale okay I
发生在R 色标上 好吧 我
guess I meant to ask if it follows from
猜猜我想问一下它是否适用
that if in your view like the the
如果在你看来 像的
molecules in the chalkboard and in my
分子在黑板上和我的
face and in the table are in any sense
无论如何，面子和桌子 都是如此
currently during doing computer I mean
目前在做电脑时 我的意思是
the question of what computation look
什么计算看起来的问题
one of the things to realize if you look
如果你看的话，要认识到的事情之一
at kind of the sort of past and future
在那种那种 过去和未来 的
of things the the
的事情
okay so here's an observation actually I
好的，所以这是 我 的观察
was about light nets actually and
实际上是和光网有关
lightning says time live Nets made a
闪电 说时间 网队做了一个
calculator type computer out of brass
黄铜计算器类型的计算机
took him 30 years okay so in his day
在他那个时代 ， 他 把他带走了30年
there was you know at most one computer
还有，你知道 最多一台电脑
in the world as far as he was concerned
就他而言 ，在世界上
right today's world there may be 10
右 今天的 世界有可能是 10
billion computers maybe 20 billion
十亿计算机可能 200亿
computers I don't know the question is
电脑我不知道问题 是什么
what's that going to look like in the
那是什么将 会是什么样 的
future and I think the answer is that in
未来，我 认为答案就 在于
time probably everything we have will be
时间大概的一切 ，我们都将 是
made of computers in the following sense
由以下意义上的计算机组成
that basically it won't be you know in
基本上你不会知道 的
today's world things are made of you
今天的世界是由你组成的
know metal plastic whatever else but
知道金属塑料除了
actually that won't make it there won't
实际上 ，这 将不会成功
be any point in doing that once we know
一旦我们知道，做任何事都是有意义的
how to do you know molecular scale
你怎么知道分子规模
manufacturing and so on we might as well
制造业等我们不妨
just make everything out of programmable
只是让所有东西都可以编程
stuff and I think that's a that's a
东西，我认为这是 一个
sense in which you know the the and you
感觉你 知道你和你
know the one example we have molecular
知道 我们有 分子 的一个例子
computing right now is us bio in biology
现在计算是生物学的生物学
you know biology does a reasonable job
你知道 生物学有一个合理的工作
of specific kinds of molecular computing
特定种类的分子 计算
it's kind of embarrassing I think that
我认为这有点令人尴尬
the only you know molecule we know that
我们知道的唯一你 知道的分子
sort of a memory molecule is DNA that's
某种记忆分子就是DNA
kind of you know which is kind of the
有种你知道这是一种 在
you know the particular biological
你知道特定 的 生物
solution in time we'll know lots of
解决方案及时我们会知道很多
others and you know I think the the sort
别人，你知道我认为那种
of the the end point is so if you're
的结束点是这样，如果你
asking is you know is computation going
问你知道的是计算进展吗？
on in you know in this water bottle the
你 知道在这个 水瓶 里吗？
answer is absolutely it's probably even
答案绝对是可能的
many aspects of that computation are
该计算的 许多方面 是
pretty sophisticated if we wanted to
相当复杂，如果我们想
know what would happen to particular
知道 会 发生 什么 特别的事情
molecules here it's going to be hard to
这里的分子很难
tell there's going to be computational
告诉 那将是计算
irreducibility and so on can we make use
我们可以使用不可减少性等
of that for our human purposes can we
为了我们的人类目的 ，我们可以
piggyback on that to achieve something
捎带， 以 实现 一些目标
technological that's different issue and
技术，这是不同的问题和
that's the four that we have to build up
这是我们必须建立的四个
this whole sort of chain of technology
这整个技术 链
to be able to connect it which is what
能够连接它是什么
I've kind of been been keep on talking
我一直在说话
about is how do we connect sort of what
关于我们如何连接什么
is possible computationally in the
在计算中是可能的
universe to what we humans can kind of
宇宙到我们人类可以的那种
conceptualize that we want to do in
概念化我们想做的事情
computation and that's you know that's
计算，那就是你知道的
the bridge that we have to make and
我们必须建造 的桥梁
that's the hard part but getting the
这是困难的部分，但得到了
intrinsic getting the computation done
内在地完成计算
is is you know there's computation going
是你知道有计算的进展
on all over the place there may be a
在所有地方可能有一个
couple more questions
更多问题
I was hoping you could elaborate on what
我希望你能详细说明 一下
you're talking about earlier of like
你之前 谈的 是喜欢的
searching the entire space of possible
搜索可能的整个空间
programs so that's very broad so maybe
程序， 所以可能非常广泛
like what kind of searching of that
喜欢什么样的搜索
space we're good at and like what we're
我们擅长的空间，就像我们一样
not and I guess what the outright so I
不， 而且我猜我是 彻头彻尾的
mean I would say that we're at an early
意思是我会说 我们处于早期阶段
stage in knowing how to do that okay so
阶段 知道怎么做， 好了，
I've done lots of these things and they
我做了很多这些事情和他们
are the thing that I've noticed is if
是我注意到的事情是
you do an exhaustive search then you
你做了详尽的 搜索
don't miss even things that you weren't
不要错过你不是的东西
looking for if you do a non exhaustive
寻找你是否做不详尽的
search there is a tremendous tendency to
搜索有一种巨大的倾向
miss things that you weren't looking for
想念你不想要的东西
and so you know we've done such as a
所以你知道我们已经完成了这样的事情
bunch of the function evaluation and
一堆功能评估和
Wolfram language is done by was done by
Wolfram语言是由完成的
searching for optimal approximations in
寻找 最优逼近
some big space a bunch of stuff with
一些大空间一堆东西
hashing is done that way bunch of image
哈希就是这样一堆图像
processing is done that way what we're
处理就是我们所做的那样
just sort of searching this you know
只是有点 搜索 你知道
doing exhaustive searches and maybe
做详尽的搜索， 也许
trillions of programs to find things now
数以万亿计的程序现在可以找到
you know there is on the other side of
你知道有对对方
that story is the incremental
这个故事是增量的
improvements story with with deep
深刻的改进故事
learning and neural networks and so on
学习和神经网络 等
where because there is differentiable
因为有可区分的地方
'ti you're able to sort of incrementally
你可以 逐步增加
get to a better solution now in fact
事实上，现在可以找到更好的解决方案
people are making less and less
人们越来越少
differentiability and deep learning
差异性和深度学习
neural nets and so I think eventually
神经网络，所以我想最终
there's going to be sort of a grand
这将是一个盛大的
unification of these kinds of approaches
统一这些方法
right now we're still you know I don't
现在我们仍然知道你不知道
really know what the you know the
真的 知道你知道什么
exhaustive search side of things which
详尽的搜索方面的东西
you can use for all sorts of purposes I
你可以用于 各种目的我
mean there's the reason the surprising
意味着令人惊讶 的 原因
thing that makes you is also search not
让 你也 搜索不到的东西
crazy is that there is rich
疯狂的是有丰富的
sophisticated stuff near at hand in the
近在咫尺的复杂东西
computational universe if you had to go
计算宇宙，如果你不得不去
you know quadrillions you know through a
你 知道通过a 知道的四分之一
quadrillion cases before you ever found
在您 找到 之前的千万亿个案例
anything the exhaustive search will be
任何详尽的搜索都将是
hopeless but you don't in many cases and
绝望但你在许多情况下并没有
you know I would say that we are in a
你知道我会说我们 在一个
fairly primitive stage of the science of
相当原始的科学阶段
how to do those searches well my guess
如何做好这些搜索我的猜测
is that there'll be some sort of
是会有某种形式的
unification which needless to say I've
不用 说 我已经统一了
thought a bunch of
想了一堆
out and between kind of than known that
出之间那种 比 知道
so you know the trade-off typically in
所以你知道 通常 的 权衡取舍
Iran that says you can have an Iran that
伊朗说你可以拥有伊朗
that is very good at that is you know
那是非常好的，你知道
uses its computational resources well
很好地利用其计算资源
but it's really hard to train or you can
但是训练真的很难， 或者你可以
have an Iran that that doesn't use its
有一个不使用它的伊朗
computational resources so well but it's
计算资源如此之好，但它是
very easy to train but this is very you
很 容易 训练，但这 就是 你
know smoothly and you know my guess is
知道得很顺利，你 知道我的猜测
that somewhere in the you know harder to
你知道的某个地方更难
train but makes use of things that are
训练， 但利用的东西
closer to the complete computational
更接近完整的计算
universe is is where one's going to see
宇宙是人们将会看到的地方
progress but it's it's a it's a really
进步，但这 是一个真的
interesting area and you know I consider
有趣的地方，你知道我考虑
us only at the at the beginning of
我们 只 在开始时
figuring that out thank you for your
搞清楚了这一点感谢您 的
talk I just to give you a bit of context
演讲中， 我只给你一些背景
for my question I research how we could
对于我的问题， 我研究如何做到
teach AI to kids and evolving platforms
向孩子和不断发展的平台教AI
for that how we could teach artificial
为此我们如何教人工
intelligence and machine learning to
智能和机器学习
children and I know you develop
孩子， 我知道你的 发展
resources for that as well so I was
对于资源，以及让我
wondering like where do you think it's
想知道你觉得它在哪里
problematic that we have computation
我们有计算的问题
that is very efficient and can do you
这非常有效， 可以帮到你
know from utilitarian and problem
从功利和 问题中得知
solving perspective it's all the goals
解决观点 是所有目标
but we don't understand how we how it
但是我们不明白我们是怎么做到的
works so we have to create the this fake
工作，所以我们必须创建这个假
steps and if you could think of
步骤，如果你能想到的话
scenarios where that could become very
可能变得非常的场景
problematic over time and why do we
随着时间的推移有问题，为什么我们
approach it such in such a deterministic
如此 确定性地接近它
way and when you mentioned that
方式，当你提到这一点
computation and intelligence are dafair
计算和智能是dafair
differentiated by this like very thin
由此非常 薄的区别
line how does that affect the way you
这行如何 影响 你 的方式
learn and how do you think that will
学习， 你 认为这将 如何
affect the way we kids learn we learn
影响 我们孩子学习 的方式
right so I mean look my general
对，所以我的意思是看我的将军
principle about you know future
关于你了解未来的原则
generations and what they should learn I
几代人以及他们应该学习什么
mean first point is you know very
意思是第一点你知道的非常
obvious point that you know for every
显而易见的一点 ，你知道每一个
field that people study you know
人们研究你知道的领域
archeology to zoology there either is
考古学到动物学那里也是
now a computational X or there will be
现在计算X 或将有
soon
不久
so you know every field the paradigm of
所以你知道每个领域的范例
computation is becoming important
计算变得越来越重要
perhaps the dominant paradigm in that
也许是 那种 主导范式
field okay so how do you teach kids to
好的，所以你怎么教孩子们
be useful in a world where everything is
在一切都是如此的世界中有用
computational I think the the number one
计算我认为头号
thing is to
事情是
each them how to think in computational
他们每个人如何 在计算中 思考
terms what does that mean that doesn't
这个术语是什么意思不是
mean writing code necessarily I mean in
意思是写代码 不一定我的意思是 在
other words one of the things that's
换句话说 这就是事情 之一
happening right now as a practical
现在作为一个实际 发生
matter is you know they've been these
问题是你知道他们就是这些
waves of enthusiasm for teaching coding
教学编码的热情
of various kinds you know we're in a
各种你知道我们在一个
we're not actually we're in the end of
我们实际上 并不是 最终的结果
an uptick wave I think it's going down
一个上升的波浪，我认为它正在下降
again um you know it's been up and down
再次嗯，你知道它一直在上下
for 40 years or so um okay why doesn't
大约 40年 左右， 好吧为什么不呢
that work well it doesn't work because
工作得很好它不起作用， 因为
while there are people like people who
虽然有人喜欢这样的人
are students at MIT for example for whom
是 麻省理工学院的 学生 ， 例如 为谁
they really want to learn you know
他们真的想学习你知道
engineering style coding and it really
工程风格编码真的
makes sense to them to learn that the
让他们了解这一点是有道理的
vast majority of people it's just not
绝大多数人都 没有
going to be relevant because they're not
因为 他们 没有相关性
going to write a low-level C program or
打算写一个低级C程序或
something and it's the same thing that's
什么东西，这是同样的事情
happened in math education which has
发生在数学教育 中
been sort of a disaster there which is
过不大不小的灾难 有哪些是
the number one takeaway for most people
大多数人的头号外卖
from the math they learn in school is I
他们在学校学到的数学 就是我
don't like math and you know that's not
不喜欢数学，你知道不是
for all of them obviously but that's the
所有这些明显的，但是 这就是
you know if you asked no general scale
你知道， 如果你没有问一般规模
you know what people and why is that
你知道什么是人，为什么会这样
well part of the reason is because
好的部分 原因是因为
what's been taught is rather low level
所教的是相当低的水平
of mechanical it's not about
机械它不是关于
mathematical thinking particularly it's
特别是数学思维
mostly about you know what teachers can
主要是关于你知道老师能做什么
teach and what assessment processes can
教导以及评估过程可以做什么
assess and so on okay so how should one
评估等等， 那么应该怎么做
teach computational thinking I mean I'm
教计算思维我的意思是我
I'm kind of excited about what we can do
我对自己 能做 什么感到很兴奋
with whorfin language because I think we
用whorfin语言因为我认为 我们
have a high enough level language that
拥有足够高级别的语言
people can actually write you know that
人们实际上可以写信给你知道
for example I I reckon by age 11 or 12
例如，我认为11岁或12岁
and I've done many experiments on this I
我已经做了很多 实验，在 此我
have some the only problem with my
我有一些唯一的 问题
experiments is most of my experiments
实验是我的大多数实验
end up being with kids who are high
最终和身处高的孩子在一起
achieving kids despite many efforts to
尽管付出了很多努
reach lower achieving kids that always
达到低成就的孩子总是
ends up that the kids who actually do
结束了实际做的孩子们
the things that I set up or the high
我设置的东西 或高
achieving kids but but you know like
实现孩子，但你知道
setting that aside
把它放在一边
you know you take the typical you know
你知道你采取你所 知道 的典型
11 12 13 year-olds and so on and they
11 12 13岁的孩子 等他们
can learn how to write stuff in this
可以学习如何 写这个东西
language and what's interesting is they
语言和有趣的是他们
learn to start thinking here I'll show
学会开始思考我会展示
you let's be very practical I can show
你让我展示 非常实用
you I was doing every Sunday I do a
你每个星期天我都在做我做的事
little little thing with some middle
一些中间的小东西
school
学校
kids and I might even be able to find my
孩子们，我甚至可以找到我的
stuff from yesterday this is this is um
从昨天的 事情这是嗯
okay let's see
好吧，让我们看看
programming adventures Janerio 28 okay
编程冒险 Janerio 28 好吧
let's see what I did
让我们看看我 做了 什么
oh look at that that was that was why I
哦，看看那这 是 这 就是为什么我
thought of the South America thing here
在这里想到了 南美的事情
because I just done that with these kids
因为我和这些孩子一起做过
the and so what are we doing we were
该所以我们在做什么，我们都
trying to figure out this this some
试图弄清楚这一点
trying to figure out the shortest tour
试图找出最短的旅程
thing like that I just showed you which
这样的事情 ，我只是 告诉你哪个
is this is where I got what you is is
这就是我得到你的地方
what I was doing with these kids but
我 和这些孩子 在做什么呢
this this was my version of this but the
这是我的版本 ，但是
kids all had various different versions
孩子们都有各种不同的版本
of this and we had somebody suggested
这个，我们有人建议
you know let's just enumerate let's just
你知道我们只是列举一下吧
look at all possible permutations of
看看所有可能的 排列
these these cities and figure out what
这些城市，并找出了什么
their distances are there's the
他们的距离还有的
histogram of those that's what we get
那些是我们得到的直方图
from those okay how do you get the
从那些没关系，你怎么得到的
largest distance from those etcetera
从这些 诸如此类 最大距离
etcetera and this is okay this was my
等等， 这是我的
version of it but the kids had similar
它的 版本， 但孩子们有类似的
stuff and this is you know this is I
东西，这就是你知道这就是 我
think and it probably went off into oh
想想， 它可能会 变成哦
yeah there we go there's there's the one
是的， 我们 去那里就是那个
for the whole whole earth and then they
对于整个地球然后他们
wanted to know how do you do that in 3d
想知道你是如何在3D中做到这一点的
so I was showing them how to convert to
所以我向他们展示了如何转换为
XYZ coordinates in 3d and make the
XYZ 在3d中坐标并制作
corresponding thing in 3d so what's this
在3d中 相应的 东西，这是什么
maybe isn't the this is a random example
也许这不是一个随机的例子
from yesterday so it's not not a highly
从昨天起，所以这不是一个高度的
considered example but but um what I
考虑的例子但却 嗯 我
think is interesting is that we seem to
觉得有趣的是 ，我们似乎
have finally reached the point where
终于达到了这 一点
we've automated enough of the actual
我们已经足够自动化了
doing of the computation that the kids
做孩子们的计算
can be exposed mostly to thinking about
大多可暴露于思考
what you might want to compute and you
你可能想要 计算 什么 和你
know part of our role in language design
了解我们在语言设计中的角色
as far as I'm concerned is to get it as
就我而言，我要担心的是
much as possible to the point where for
尽可能多的地方
example you can do a bunch of natural
例如 你可以做一堆自然的
language input you can do things which
语言输入，你 可以做的事情 ，
make it as easy as possible for kids to
让它尽可能容易 为 孩子们
not get mixed up in the kind of what the
不要混淆在什么样的
you know how the computation gets done
你知道如何完成计算
but rather to just think about how you
而是想想你是怎么做的
formulate the computation so for example
制定 这样 的计算 ， 例如
a typical example I've used much times
我 用了很多次的典型例子
in you know what does it mean to do
在你知道这意味着 什么
write code versus two other
写代码与另外两个
things like a typical set of test
像一套典型的测试
example would be I don't know you ask
例如， 我不知道你 问
somebody you're gonna there's practical
有人你会在那里实用
problem we had in wolf's mouth you give
我们在狼的 嘴里 给你的问题
a lat long position on the earth and you
地球上的一个长长的位置 和你
say you're gonna make a map of that like
说你 要制作一张那样的地图
long position what what scale of map
多头位置什么规模的地图
should you make alright so if the
如果你 做得好， 你应该好吗？
lat/long is in the middle of the Pacific
lat / long位于太平洋中部
making a ten mile
十英里
you know radius map isn't very
你知道半径图不是很好
interesting if it's in the middle of
有趣的是， 如果它在中间
Manhattan a 10-mile radius map might be
曼哈顿半径10英里的地图可能是
quite quite a sensible thing to do so
相当相当明智的做法 使
the question is come up with an
问题是 想出一个
algorithm come up with even a way of
算法提出了一种方法
thinking about that question what do you
思考那个问题你是做什么的
do you know how should you figure that
你知道怎么想的吗？
out well you might say you know oh let's
好吧你可能会说你知道哦，让我们
look at the visual complexity of the
看看视觉的复杂性
image let's look at how far it is to
图像让我们来看看它 是多远
another city let's fight you know there
另一个城市让你在那里打架
various different things but thinking
各种不同的事情，但思考
about that as a kind of computational
关于那作为一种计算
thinking exercise that term is you know
思考练习 那个词是你知道的
that's the kind of thing so in terms of
这就是那种事情
what one automates and whether people
什么人自动化，是否人
whether people need to understand how it
人们是否需要了解它是如何理解的
works inside okay main point is you'll
内部工作好 主要是 你会
in the end it will not be possible to
最终它是不可能的
know how it works inside so you might as
知道它是如何工作的 ，所以你可能会这样
well stop having that be a criterion I
好吧，那就是我的标准
mean that is there plenty of things that
意味着有很多的 东西，
one teaches people that let's say in
一个教人们说让我们说
lots of areas of biology medicine
大量的生物 医药 领域
whatever else you know maybe we'll know
不管你知道什么，也许我们都知道
how it works inside one day but you can
如何在一天内工作， 但 你可以
still there's an awful lot of useful
还有很多 有用的东西
stuff you can teach without knowing how
你可以教的东西， 不知道怎么做
it works inside and I think also as we
它在里面工作 ，我想也 像我们一样
get computation to be more efficient
让计算更有效率
inevitably we will be dealing with
不可避免地，我们将处理
things where you don't know how it works
你不知道它是如何工作的东西
inside now you know we've seen this in
现在你知道我们已经看到了这个
math education because I've happened to
数学教育，因为 我碰巧
made tools that automate a bunch of
制作工具，自动化一堆
things that people do in math education
人们在数学教育中所做的 事情
and I think well to tell a silly story
我想好好讲一个愚蠢的故事
I'm in my my older daughter who at some
我在我的大女儿身上
point in the past was doing you know
过去的一点是让你 知道
calculus you know and learning doing
微积分你知道和学习 做
integrals and things and I was saying to
我正在说积分和事物
her you know I didn't think humans still
她知道我不认为人类还在
did that stuff anymore which was a very
这样做的东西了 这是 一个 非常
unintelligent fit but in any case I mean
不合情 合适，但无论如何我的意思是
the the you know there's a question of
你知道有一个问题
whether do humans need to know how to do
人类是否需要知道该怎么做
that stuff or not so I haven't done an
那东西与否， 所以我没有做过
integral by hand and probably thirty
手工积分，大概三十
five years
5年
a true more or less true then but when I
真正或多或少真，那么但当我
was using computers to do them the I was
我是用电脑做的
for a while you know I used to do
你知道我曾经做过一段时间
physics and so I used computers to do
物理等我用电脑 做的
this stuff I was a really really good
这个东西我真的很棒
integrator except that it wasn't really
积分器除了它不是真的
me it was me plus the computer so how
我是我加上 电脑 所以如何
did that come to be
那是怎么回事
well the answer was that because I was
答案是， 因为我是
doing things by computer I was able to
通过计算机做事我能够
try zillions of examples and I got a
尝试数以万计的例子，我得到了一个
much better intuition the most people
大多数 人的直觉要好得多
got for how these things would work
得到了这些东西是如何工作的
roughly how what you did to make the
大概你是怎么做的
thing go and so on whereas people who
东西去等等而不是那些人
are like I'm just working this one thing
就像我只是 在做这件事
out by hand
手工拿出来
you got a different you know you don't
你有一个不同的， 你知道你没有
get that intuition so I think you know
得到那种直觉所以我想你知道
two points first of all you know this
两点首先你知道 这一点
how do you think about things
你怎么看待事情
computationally how do you formulate the
计算你如何制定
question computationally that's really
在计算上问这是真的
important and something that we are now
重要的，我们现在的东西
in a position I think to actually teach
在我认为 实际教学 的位置
and it is not really something you teach
这不是你教的东西
by you know teaching you know
通过你知道教你知道
traditional quotes coding because a lot
传统的报价编码因为很多
of that is okay we're gonna make a loop
那是好的 我们要做一个循环
we're going to define variables I just
我们将仅仅定义变量
as I think I probably have a copy here
我想我可能 在这里有一份副本
yeah they I wrote this book for this is
是的 ，我为此写了这本书
a book kind of for kids about often
一本书， 一种关于孩子们 经常
language except it seems to be useful to
除了它的语言 似乎是 有用的
adults as well but I wrote it for kids
大人也是，但我 是为孩子们 写的
so it's some and one of the amusing
所以它是一些和一个有趣的
things in this book is it doesn't
这本书中的内容是不是
talking it talked about assigning values
谈论它谈论分配价值
to variables until chapter 38 so in
到变量， 直到第38章如此
other words that will be a thing that
换句话说，这将 是一个事情 ，
you would find in Chapter one of most
你会发现在 一个章 的最
you know low-level programming coding
你知道低级编程 编码
type type things turns out it's not that
键入类的东西原来， 这并不是 说
relevant to know how to do that it's
相关知道如何做到这 一点
also kind of confusing and not necessary
也有点混乱，没有必要
and so you know in terms of the you
所以你知道你的意思
asked where will we get in trouble when
问我们什么时候会遇到麻烦
people don't know how the stuff works
人们不 知道这些东西是如何运作的
inside that's I mean you know I think
在里面， 我的意思是你知道我在想
one just has to get used to that because
一个人只需要习惯那个因为
it's like you know you might say well we
就像你知道 你可能会 说得好
live in the world and it's full of
生活在这个世界上，它充满了
natural processes where we don't know
我们不知道的 自然 过程
how they work inside but somehow we
他们如何在里面工作，但不知何故我们
manage to survive and we go to a lot of
设法 生存，我们去了很多
effort to do natural science to try and
努力 做自然科学尝试和
figure out how stuff works inside but it
弄清楚东西是如何工作的但是它
turns out we can still use plenty of
结果我们仍然可以使用大量的
things even when we don't know how they
即使我们不知道他们是怎么回事
work inside we don't need to know
在里面工作我们不需要知道
and I think the May I think the main
而且我认为 五月我认为主要
point is computational irreducibility
点是计算不可约性
guarantees that we will be using things
保证我们会使用 东西
where we don't know and can't know how
在哪里我们不知道， 也不知道如何
they work inside and you know I think
他们在里面工作，你知道我认为
the the perhaps the thing that is a
这是一个 对的 也许 是事
little bit you know to me a little bit
你有点了解我的一点点
unfortunate as a you know as a typical
不幸的是，你知道这是一个典型的
human type thing the fact that I can
人类型事物我能做到的事实
readily see that you know the AI stuff
很容易看出 你知道 AI的东西
we build is sort of effectively creating
我们建立的是一种有效的创造
languages and things that are completely
完全是语言和事物
outside our domain to understand and
在我们的域外了解 和
we're by that I mean you know our human
我们的意思是你知道我们的人类
language with its fifty thousand words
语言有它的 五万字
or whatever has been developed over the
或者 已经开发的任何东西
last however many you know tens of
但是 很多人知道几十个
thousands of years and as a society
几千年来，作为一个社会
we've developed this way of
我们开发了这种方式
communicating and explaining things you
沟通和解释你的事情
know the AIS are reproducing that
知道AIS 正在复制那个
process very quickly but they're coming
过程非常快，但 他们来了
up with a and a historical you know
了 一个，你知道历史
something you know their way of
你知道他们的方式
describing the world that doesn't happen
描述未发生的世界
to relate at all to our historical way
完全与我们的历史方式联系起来
of doing it and that's you know it's a
这样做，你知道这是一个
little bit disquieting to me as a human
作为一个人，我有点不安
that that you know there are things
那你知道有事情
going on inside where I know it is you
走进 我认识的地方就是你
know in principle I could learn that
我原则上知道我可以学到这一点
language but it's you know not the
语言，但你知道的不是
historical one that we've all learnt and
我们都学过的历史性的
it really wouldn't make a lot of sense
它真的不会有多大 意义
to do that because you learn it for one
这样做 是因为你为一个人学习
AI and then another one gets trained and
AI然后另一个人接受训练
it's going to use something different so
它会使用 不同的东西
it's some but my main I guess my main
它是一些但我的主要我想我的主要
point for for education another point
教育的另一点
about education I just make which is
关于我刚才做的教育
something I haven't figured out but but
我还没想到的东西，但是
um just is you know when do we get to
嗯， 你知道我们什么时候到达
make a good model for the human learner
为人类学习者打造一个好榜样
using machine learning so in other words
换句话说，使用机器学习
you know part of what we're trying to do
你知道我们 要做的事情的一部分
like like I've got that automated proof
就像我有自动证明一样
I would really like to manage to figure
我真的想 设法 图
out a way what is the best way to
这是一种最好的方式
present that proof so a human can
提出 一个人类可以证明的证据
understand it and basically for that we
理解它， 基本上就是我们
have to have a bunch of heuristics about
必须有一个关于一群启发式的
how humans understand things so as an
人类是如何理解的事情，以便为
example if we're doing let's say a lot
例如，如果我们做 了很多话
of visualization stuff in welcomed
受欢迎的可视化内容
language okay we have tried to automate
语言好吧我们试图 自动化
do automated aesthetics so what we're
做自动化美学所以我们是什么
doing is you know we're laying out a
干嘛，你知道我们正在布置一个
graph what way of laying out that graph
绘制图表的布局方式
is most likely for humans to understand
人类最有可能理解
and we've done that you know by building
我们已经完成了你所知道的建设
a bunch of heuristics and so on but
一堆启发式 等 ，但
that's an example of you know if we
这 是你 知道我们 的一个 例子
could do that for learning and we say
能做到这一点的 学习 和我们说
what's the optimal path given that the
什么是考虑到最优路径
person is trying to understand this
人正在试图 理解这一点
proof for example what's the optimal
证明例如什么是最优的
path to lead them through understanding
引导他们理解的道路
that proof I suspect we will learn a lot
这个证据我怀疑我们会 学到很多东西
more in probably a fairly small number
更多可能是一个 相当小的数字
of years about that and it will be the
多年来，这将是
case that you know for example if you've
你知道的情况， 例如你是否已经知道
got oh I don't know you can do simple
得到 哦我不知道你能做到简单
things like you know you go to Wikipedia
像你这样的人 知道 你去 了维基百科
and you look at what the path of you
你看看你的道路是什么
know how do you if you want to learn
如果你想学习，你知道怎么做
this concept what other concepts you
这个概念你还有什么其他概念
have to learn we have much more detailed
必须学习我们有更详细的
symbolic information about what is
关于什么是象征性的信息
actually necessary to know in order to
实际上有必要 知道 为了
understand this and so on it is I think
我想是明白这个等等
reasonably likely that we will be able
我们 很可能 会这样做
to I mean you know if I look at I was
我的 意思是 你知道 我 是 不是看着我
interested recently in the history of
最近感兴趣的是历史
math education so I wanted to look at
数学教育让我想 看看
the complete sort of path of math
完整的数学路径
textbooks you know for the past well
你过去认识的教科书
basically the like twelve hundred you
基本上像你这样的一百二十
know people actually produced this one
知道人们实际上 生产了这个
of the early math textbooks so they've
早期的数学教科书， 所以他们
been these different ways of teaching
这些 不同的教学方式
math and you know I think we've we've
数学，你知道我认为我们已经
gradually evolved a fairly optimized way
逐步演变出一种相当优化的方式
for the typical person though it's
对于典型的人来说 虽然如此
probably the variation of the population
可能 是人口 的变化
is not well understood for you know how
不能很好 地理解你知道如何
to explain certain concepts and we've
解释某些概念，我们已经
gone through some pretty weird ways of
经历了一些非常奇怪的方式
doing it from the 1600s and so on
从17世纪开始这样做
where which have gone out of style and
其中已经出去的风格 和
possibly you know who knows whether
可能你知道谁知道是否
that's versus because of well but anyway
这是因为 与 井，但无论如何
so so you know we've kind of learnt this
所以你知道我们已经 学到了这一点
path of what's the optimal way to
什么是最佳方式的路径
explain adding fractions or something
解释添加分数或其他东西
for humans for the typical human but I
对于典型的人而言我是人类
think we'll learn a lot more about how
认为我们会学到更多 有关如何
you know by by essentially making a
你知道通过基本上制作一个
model for the human a machine model for
人体 模型的机器模型
the human we'll learn more about how to
人类我们将更多地了解 如何
you know how to optimize how to explain
你知道如何优化如何解释
stuff to humans a coming attraction but
对人类来说是个吸引人的东西但是
Tim thanks by the way do you think we're
蒂姆感谢 你认为我们 的 方式
close to that at all because you you
因为你，所以接近这一点
said that there's a something in Wolfram
说Wolfram 有 一些东西
Alpha that that presents the human a
提出 人类的阿尔法
nice way are we how far said attraction
好的方式是我们说 吸引力有 多远
yeah right so I mean in in that
是的， 所以我的意思是
explaining stuff to humans thing is a
向人类解释的东西是一个
lot of human work right now being able
大量的人力工作的，现在能
to automate
自动化
explaining stuff to humans okay so some
向人类解释的东西 还好吧
of these things let's see I mean so an
这些东西让我们看到我的意思是这样的
interesting question actually just today
有趣的问题实际上 只是今天
I was working on something that's
我正在做一些事情
related to this yeah it's it's it's
与 此 相关 是的，就是这样
being able to the question is given a
能够提出这个问题
whole bunch of can we for example train
一大堆我们可以举例如火车
a machine learning system from
一个机器学习系统
explanations that it can see roughly can
它可以看到的解释大致可以
we train it to give explanations that
我们训练它来解释
are likely to be understandable maybe I
也许我可能是可以理解的
think the okay so an example that I'd
想好了，所以一个 例子 ，我会
like to do okay I'd like to do a
喜欢做好 我 想做一个
debugging assistant where the typical
调试助手哪里有典型
thing is program runs program gives
事情是程序运行程序给出的
wrong answer human says why did you get
错误的答案人类说你为什么得到
the wrong why did it give the wrong
错误的原因是它给出了错误
answer well the first piece of
回答 第一部分
information to the computer is that was
那是 给 计算机的信息
the human thought that was the wrong
人类的思想是 错误的
answer because the computer just did
回答是因为电脑刚刚做了
what it was told and it didn't know that
是什么被告知，它不知道
was supposed to be the wrong answer so
被 认为是 错误的答案 ，以便
then the question is can you in fact you
那么你的问题就是你
know in that domain can you actually
你真的知道那个领域吗？
have a reasonable conversation in which
有一个合理的 对话 中，
the human is explaining the computer
人类正在解释计算机
what they thought it was supposed to do
他们认为应该怎么做
the computer is explaining what happened
电脑正在解释发生的事情
and why did it happen and so on same
为什么会 发生这样的事情呢？
kind of thing for math tutoring you know
数学家辅导 你 知道 的 事情
we have a lot of you know we've got a
我们有很多人都知道我们有一个
lot of stuff you know we're sort of very
很多东西，你 知道我们有点 非常
widely used for people who want to
广泛用于 谁想要 的人
understand the steps in math you know
了解你 知道的 数学步骤
can we make a thing where people tell us
我们可以做人们告诉 我们 的事情
I think it's this okay I'll tell you one
我想这没关系，我会告诉 你一个
one little factoid which I which you did
我做过的一个小事实
work out so if you do multi digit
如果你做了多位数，那就搞定了
arithmetic multi-digit addition okay
算术多位数加法好吧
okay so the basis of this is its kind of
好的，所以这个的基础是它的那种
silly silly thing but you know if you
愚蠢的傻事， 但你 知道吗
get the right answer for an addition
得到正确 答案 的补充
some okay you don't get very much
有些没关系， 你不会得到太多
information the student gives the wrong
学生 错误的信息
answer the question is can you tell them
回答问题是你能告诉他们吗？
where they went wrong so let's say you
他们出错的地方让我们说你
have a four digit addition sum and the
有一个四位数的加法和和
student gives the wrong answer can you
学生给出了错误的答案 ，你可以
back trace and figure out what they
回溯并弄清楚他们是什么
likely did wrong and the answer is you
可能做错了， 答案就是你
can you know you just make this graph of
你能知道你 只是 制作这张图 吗？
all the different things that can happen
所有 可能 发生 的不同 事情
you know when did they you know there's
你 知道 他们 什么时候 知道的
certain things that are more common
某些更 常见的事情
transposing numbers and things or you
转置数字和事物或你
know having a 1 and a 7 mixed up those
知道有一个和一个混合了那些
kinds of things you can with very high
你 可以 用非常高的东西
power let's say given a for de division
权力让我们说给予分裂
some with the wrong answer you can say
你可以说有些错误的答案
this is the mistake you made
这是你 犯 的错误
which is sort of interesting and that's
这是有点 有趣，这就是
you know being done in a fairly symbolic
你知道这是一个相当具有象征意义的人
way whether one can do that in a you
是否可以在你身上做到这一点
know more machine learning kind of way
知道更多的机器学习方式
for more complicated derivations I'm not
对于更复杂的 派生，我不是
sure but that's a that's one that works
当然， 但这是 一个有效的
are you sir I just had a follow-up
你是先生我 刚跟进了吗？
question so do you think you know like
问题你认为 你知道 吗？
in the future this is it possible to
在未来 ， 这是 有可能
simulate virtual environments which can
模拟可以的虚拟环境
actually understand how the human mind
其实了解 的 人的心灵
works and then build you know like
工作 ，然后建立你知道的喜欢
finite state machines inside of this
这里有限状态机
virtual environment to provide a better
虚拟环境提供更好的
learning experience and a more
学习经验和更多
personalized learning experience well I
个性化的学习经历我
mean so the question is if if you're
这意味着问题是，如果你是
going to you know can you optimize if
去找你知道你能优化吗？
you're playing a video game or something
你正在玩视频 游戏 什么的
and that video game is supposed to be
那个视频游戏应该是
educational can you optimize the the
教育你可以优化
experience based on a model of you so to
基于你的模型的经验
speak yeah I'm sure the answer is yes
说 是的我 确定 答案是肯定的
and I'm sure the you know the question
我敢肯定，你知道的问题
of how complicated the model of you will
你的模型会有多复杂
be is an interesting question I don't
是一个有趣的问题， 我没有
know the answer to I mean I've I've kind
知道 答案， 我的意思是我很善良
of wanted a similar question so I I'm a
想要一个类似的问题，所以我就是一个
kind of personal analytics enthusiast so
那种个人分析爱好者
I collect tons of data about myself and
我收集了大量 关于我自己 的数据
I mean I do it mostly because it's been
我的意思是我这样做主要是因为它已经存在
super easy to do and I've done it for
超级容易做，我已经做到 了
like 30 years and I have you know every
像30年 ， 我知道每一个
keystroke I've typed on a computer like
击键我输入电脑 一样 ，
every keystroke I've typed here and I
我在这里输入的每次击键和我
the screen of my computer every every 30
我的电脑屏幕每隔30个
seconds or so of maybe 15 seconds I'm
秒左右 的也许15秒我
not sure it there's a screen shot it's a
不确定它有一个屏幕截图 它是一个
super boring movie to watch but anyway
无论如何， 要观看超级无聊的电影
I've been collecting all this stuff and
我一直在收集所有这些东西
so a question that I've asked is is
所以我问过的问题 是
there enough data that a bot of me could
有足够的数据 ，我的机器人可以
be made in other words do I have enough
换句话说制成 做我有足够的
data about you know I've got I've
关于你的数据我知道我已经拥有了
written a million emails I have all of
我写了一百万封电子邮件
those I've received three million emails
那些我收到了300万封电子邮件
over that period of time I've got you
在那段时间里， 我有你
know endless you know things I've typed
知道无数你知道我输入的东西
etc etcetera etcetera you know is there
等你 知道的等等等等
enough data to reconstruct you know me
足够的数据重建你了解我
basically I think the answer is probably
基本上我认为 答案可能是
yes not sure but I think the answer is
是的不确定， 但我 认为答案是
probably yes and so the question is in
可能是的，所以问题在于
an environment where you are interacting
您正在互动的环境
with some video game trying to learn
一些 视频 游戏努力学习
something whatever else you know
什么你知道的东西
how long is it going to be before it can
究竟是怎样长成之后 才能
learn enough about you to change that
足够了解你改变它
environment in a way that's useful for
环境以一种 有用的方式
explaining the next thing to you I would
我会向你解释下一件事
guess I would guess that have done that
猜猜我猜这已经做到了
this is comparatively easy I might be
这 可能 比较 容易
wrong but that and that the I mean I
错了，但那就是 我的意思
think you know it's an interesting thing
认为你知道这是一件有趣的事情
because you know once dealing with you
因为你知道曾经 和你打交道
know there's a space of human
知道有一个人的空间
personalities there's a space of human
个性有一个人的空间
learning styles you know I'm sort of
学习风格，你知道我有点
always interested in the space of all
总是对所有人 的空间感兴趣
possible XYZ and there's you know
可能的XYZ，你知道吗？
there's that question over how do you
有 过 你怎么 这个问题
parameterize the space of all possible
参数化所有可能的空间
human learning styles and is there a way
人类的学习风格，有没有办法
that we will learn you know like can we
我们 将学习你想知道 我们 能
do that symbolically and say these are
做到这一点象征性地说，这些 都是
ten learning styles or is it something I
十种 学习方式或者是我的东西
think that's a case where it's better to
认为这是一个 更好 的情况
use you know sort of soft machine
用你知道一种软机
learning type methods to kind of feel
学习型的方法有种感觉
out that space well you know maybe very
你知道的那个空间很好
last question I was just intuitively
最后一个问题我只是直觉上
thinking when you spoke about an ocean I
想着当你谈到 的海洋我
thought of Isaac Newton when he said I
当艾萨克· 牛顿说我的时候想到了艾萨克· 牛顿
mean you know the famous quote I might
意思是你知道 我可能的名言
not and I thought instead of Newton on
没有，我想而不是牛顿
the beach what if franz liszt were there
如果franz liszt在那里，那该海滩怎么样？
what question would he ask what would he
他会问他会是什么问题
say
说
and I'm trying to understand you're the
而我正在努力理解你是谁
alien ocean and humans through maybe
外星人的海洋和人类通过也许
Franz Liszt and music well so I mean the
弗朗茨李斯特和音乐很好，所以我的意思 是
the quote from Newton is is some sort of
牛顿 的引用 是 某种 形式的
an interesting quote I think it goes
我 认为这 是一个有趣的引用
something like this if you know people
这样的事情 ，如果你认识的人
are talking about how wonderful calculus
正在谈论微妙的微积分
and all that kind of thing are and
所有这些事情 都是和
Newton says you know to others I may
牛顿说你可能对别人了解
seem like I've done a lot of stuff but
好像我 做了很多东西但是
to me I seem like a child who who picked
对我来说，我似乎是一个挑选的孩子
up a particularly elegant you know
你知道，特别优雅
seashell on the on the beach and I've
我在海滩上的贝壳
been studying this this seashell for a
一直在研究这个贝壳
while even though there's this ocean of
而即使有 这个海洋
truth out there waiting to be discovered
真相在那里等待 被发现
that's roughly the quote okay
这大致 是报价好的
I find that quote interesting for the
我觉得这句话很有意思
following reason the what Newton did was
以下原因是牛顿所做的
you know calculus and things like
你知道微积分和类似的东西
kit if you look at the computational
如果你看看计算的工具包
universe of all possible programs there
那里所有可能的程序的宇宙
is a small corner Newton was exactly
是牛顿的 一个小角落
right and what he said that is he picked
对 ，他说的是他挑选的
off calculus which is a corner of the
离演算这是的一个角落
possible things that can happen in the
可能发生的事情
computational universe that happened to
正巧计算宇宙
be an elegant seashell so to speak they
是一个优雅的贝壳，可以这么说
happened to be a case where you can
发生在那里 你可以 成为一个案例
figure out what's going on and and so on
弄清楚是怎么回事 ，并等
while there is still a sort of ocean of
虽然还有一种海洋
of other sort of computational
其他类型的计算
possibilities out there but but when it
那里的可能性， 但是当它
comes to you know you're asking about
谈到你知道你问
music I I think my computer stopped
我的音乐我 觉得我的电脑 停止
being able to get anywhere but but um
能够到达但是嗯
sort of interesting the cific get to the
一点点有趣的cific到达
site yeah so this is a this is a website
网站是啊，所以这是 一个这是 一个 网站
that we made years ago and now my
我们多年前做的 ，现在是我的
computer isn't playing anything but
电脑是不是在玩什么，但
[Music]
[音乐]
let's try that okay so these things are
让我们试试 这些 事情就好了
created by basically just searching
通过基本上只是搜索创建
computational universe for possible
可能的计算宇宙
programs it's sort of interesting
程序有点有趣
because everyone has kind of a story
因为每个人都有一个故事
some of them are look more interesting
他们中的一些 看起来更有趣
than others let's try that one
比起其他人让我们尝试那个
anyway the the what's what's interesting
无论如何， 有趣的是什么
actually what was interesting to me
实际上 对 我来说 很有趣
about this was this is a very trivial
关于这一点，这 是非常微不足道的
you know what this is doing is very
你知道这是做什么的很
trivial at some level it's just it
在某种程度上微不足道就是它
actually happens to use cellular
实际上碰巧使用细胞
automata you can even have it show you I
自动机你甚至可以 告诉我我
think someplace here where is it
想到这里某处 它在哪里
somewhere there's a way of showing your
某处有一种展示你的方式
show the evolution this is this is
展示这 就是这个演变
showing the behind the scenes what was
显示幕后是什么
actually happening what it chose to use
实际上发生了它选择使用的东西
to generate that musical piece um and
生成那首音乐作品
what I thought was interesting about the
我认为有趣的是
site I thought well you know how would
网站我认为你知道怎么会
computers be relevant to music etcetera
计算机与音乐等相关
etcetera etcetera well you know what
etcetera etcetera你知道吗
would happen is a human would have an
会发生的是 人类会有的
idea and then the computer would kind of
想法，然后计算机会有点
dressup that idea and then you know a
装扮那个想法，然后你就知道了
bunch of years go by and I talked to
一堆年过去和我 交谈过
people you know who composers and things
你认识的 人 谁作曲家和事
and they say oh yeah I really like that
他们说哦，是的，我真的很喜欢
wolfram tones site okay that's nice they
wolfram 色调网站好吧，他们很好
say it's a very good place for me to get
说这对我来说是一个非常好的地方
ideas so that's sort of the opposite of
这些想法 恰恰相反
what I would have expected namely what's
我 本来期望就是什么
happening is you know human comes here
发生在你知道人类来到这里
you know listens to some 10-second
你知道 听了大约10秒钟
fragment and they said oh that's an
片段，他们说哦，那是一个
interesting idea and then they kind of
有趣的想法，然后他们那种
embellish it using kind of something
使用某种东西来修饰它
that is humanly meaningful but it's like
这是 有人 意义的，但 它就像
you know you're taking a photograph and
你知道你在 拍照 和
you see some interesting configuration
你看到一些有趣的配置
and then kind of you're you know you're
然后你就知道你了
filling that with kind of some human
填充与某些 种类的 人
sort of context but but so I'm not quite
上下文，但所以我不是
sure what what you were asking about I I
确定你在问我 什么
mean back to the Newton quote the thing
意味着回到牛顿引用的东西
that I think is some another way to
我认为是另一种方式
think about that quote is us humans you
想想 那 句话就是我们人类你
know with our sort of historical
知道我们的历史
development of you know our intellectual
发展你知道我们的知识分子
history have explored this very small
历史探索这个非常小
corner of what's possible in the
是什么 在 可能的角落
computational universe and everything
计算宇宙和一切
that we care about is contained in the
我们 关心 的 是包含在
small corner and that means that you
小角落，这意味着你
know you could say well gee you know I
知道你可以说得很好， 你 知道我
want to you know what we what we end up
想你知道我们是什么 ，我们结束 了
wanting to talk about other things that
想 谈其他 的事情 ，
we as a society
我们作为一个社会
have decided we care about and what
已决定 我们关心什么
there's an interesting feedback loop I
有一个有趣的反馈回路 我
just mentioned mr. den but but um so you
刚提到的先生。但是，但是你，所以你
might say so here's a funny thing so
可能会这么说，所以这是一个有趣的事情
let's take language for example language
让我们举个例子language语言
evolves we you say we we make up
进化我们你说我们弥补
language to describe what we see in the
语言来描述我们在中看到的东西
world okay fine
世界还好
that's a fine idea imagine the you know
这个好主意想象你知道
in Paleolithic times people make up
在旧石器时代人们弥补
language they probably didn't have a
语言，他们可能没有 一个
word for table because they didn't have
字表，因为他们没有
any tables they probably had a word for
他们可能有一个词的任何表格
rock but then we end up as a result of
岩石但我们最终成为的 结果
the particular you know development that
具体的，你知道那发展
our civilization has gone through we
我们的文明经历了我们
build tables and there was sort of a
构建表格， 有点像
synergy between coming up with a word
提出一个词之间的协同作用
for table and deciding tables were a
对于表和决定表是一个
thing and we should build a bunch of
事情，我们应该建立 一堆
them and so there's a sort of
他们，所以有几分
complicated interplay between the things
事物之间复杂的相互作用
that we learn how to describe and how to
我们学习如何描述和如何描述
think about the things that we build and
想一想 ，我们建立 和 事
put in our environment and then the
放入我们的环境，然后
things that we end up wanting to talk
我们最终想要谈论的事情
about because they're things that we
因为他们是 我们的 事情
have experience of in our environment
有我们环境的经验
and so that's the you know I think as we
所以你知道我认为就像我们一样
look at sort of the progress of
看看那种 进步
civilization there's you know there's
文明，你知道那里有
various layers of first we you know we
各种各样的层次我们你知道我们
invent a thing that we can then think
发明一个我们可以 思考的东西
about and talk about then we build an
关于并谈论 我们建立一个
environment based on that then that
基于那样的环境
allows us to do more stuff and we build
允许我们 做更多的 事情，我们建立
on top of that and that's why for
除此之外， 这就是 为什么
example when we talk about computational
我们谈论计算的例子
thinking and teaching it to kids and so
思考和教导孩子等等
on that's one reason that's kind of
在这一个原因，就是 那种
important because we're building a layer
很重要， 因为我们正在 构建一个图层
of things that people are then familiar
人们熟悉的事情
with that's different from what we've
与我们的不同
had so far and they give people a way to
到目前为止 ，已经和 他们给人 一种方式
talk about things I give you one example
谈谈我给你举个 例子的 事情
that um see that I have that still up
那我看到我还有这个
the okay one one one example here from
好的， 这里的 一个例子
this blog post of mine actually so there
我的这个博客帖子居然 这么有
okay so that that thing there is a
好的，那样的东西就有了
nested pattern you know it's a bitter
嵌套模式你知道它是一个 苦涩的
sierpinski that that tile pattern was
sierpinski 那个瓷砖图案是
created in 1210 ad okay and it's the
在1210年创建广告还可以
first example I know of a fractal
第一个例子我知道一个分形
pattern okay
模式没关系
well the art historians wrote about
艺术史学家写的很好
these patterns they're a bunch of this
这些模式 他们是一堆这样的
particular style of pattern they wrote
他们写的特殊模式
about these for years they never
关于这些 多年来他们从来没有
discussed that nested pattern these
讨论了 嵌套图案 这些
patterns also have you know pictures of
图案也让你知道图片
lions and then you know elephants and
狮子，然后你知道大象和
things like that on them they wrote
他们写的 东西就是这样
about those kinds of things but they
关于那些 事情，但他们
never mentioned the nested pattern until
从来没有提到过嵌套模式
basically about 25 years ago when
基本上大约25年前的时候
fractals and so on became a thing and
分形等等变成了事物
then it's ah I can now talk about that
那是啊我现在可以谈论这个了
it's a nested pattern it's fractal and
它是一个嵌套模式， 它是分形的
then you know before that time the art
然后你就知道那个 时代 之前 的艺术
historians were blind to that particular
历史学家对这一点视而不见
part of this pattern it's just like I
这个模式 的一部分， 它就像我
don't know what that is that there's no
不 知道那是什么， 没有
you know I don't have a word to describe
你知道我 没有 一句话要形容
it I'm not going to I'm not going to
但我不会，我 不会去
talk about it so that's a you know it's
谈论它，这是你知道的
part of this feedback loop of things
的东西，这个反馈回路 的一部分
that we we learn to describe then we
我们学会描述然后我们
build in terms of those things then we
根据那些事情建立我们
build another layer I think one of the
建立另一层我认为其中之一
things I mean you talk about you know
我的意思是你说你 知道的事情
just in the sort of the thing like one
只是在 有点 像一个东西
thing I'm really interested in is the
我真正感兴趣的是
evolution of purposes so you know if you
目的的演变， 所以你知道你是否
look back in human history there's a you
回顾人类历史，有一个你
know what was thought to be worth doing
知道什么被认为值得做
a thousand years ago it's different from
一千年前 ， 它是 从 不同
what's thought to be worth doing today
什么被认为值得做今天
and part of that is is you know good
部分 原因是你 知道的 很好
examples of things like you know walking
你 知道走路的例子
on a treadmill or buying goods in
在跑步机上或购买商品
virtual worlds both of these are hard to
虚拟世界这两者 都很难
explain to somebody from a thousand
从 千人 向某人解释
years ago because each one ends up being
几年 前，因为 每个人最终都是
a whole sort of societal story about
一整套关于社会的故事
we're doing this because we do that
我们这样做是因为我们这样做
because we do that and so the question
因为我们这样做， 所以 问题
is how will these purposes evolve in the
这些目的将如何演变
future and I think one of the things
未来我认为其中的一件事
that I view as a sort of sobering
我认为这是一种发人深省的态度
thought is that that term actually one
以为那个词 实际上是一个
thing I found other disappointing and
我发现其他令人失望的事情
then I became less pessimistic about it
然后我变得不那么悲观了
is if you think about the future of the
是，如果你 想 的 未来
human condition and you know we've been
人类的状况 ，你知道我们一直在
successful in making our AI systems and
成功制作我们的AI系统和
we can read out brains and we can upload
我们可以读出大脑，我们可以上传
consciousnesses and things like that and
意识之类的东西，并
we've eventually got this box with
我们最终得到了这个盒子
trillions of souls and
数以万亿计的灵魂和灵魂
and the question is what are these souls
问题是这些灵魂是什么
doing and to us today it looks like
今天做和我们一起看起来像
they're playing video games to the rest
他们正在玩电子 游戏
of eternity right and that seems like a
永恒的权利，这似乎是 一个
kind of a bad outcome it's like we've
这是一种糟糕的结果，就像我们一样
gone through all of this long history
通过所有 这漫长的历程
and what do we end up with we end up
和做什么，我们结束了 我们结束了
with a trillion souls in a box playing
在一个盒子里玩着万亿灵魂
video games okay um and I thought this
电子游戏好吧， 我想到了这一点
is a very you know depressing outcome so
你是一个非常令人沮丧的结果
to speak and then I realized that that
发言然后我才意识到这一点
actually you know if you look at the
实际上你 知道如果你看看
sort of arc of human history people
那种人类 历史 的人 的圆弧
aren't any given time in history people
历史上没有任何特定时间的人
have been you know they've my main
你知道他们是我的主力吗？
conclusion is that any time in history
结论是历史上的任何时候
the things people do seem meaningful and
人们做的事似乎有意义
purposeful to them at that time in
那个时候对他们有目的的
history and history moves on and you
历史和历史继续前进和你
know like a thousand years ago there
知道就像一千年前 那里
were a lot of purposes that people had
人们有很多目的
that you know what to do with weird
你知道如何处理奇怪的事情
superstitions and things like that that
迷信和类似的东西
we say why the heck are you doing that
我们说为什么赫克要那样做
that just doesn't make any sense
这没有 任何 意义
right but to them at that time it made
它是对的，但它在那个 时候
all the sense in the world and I think
我 认为 世界上所有的意义
that you know the thing that makes me
你知道 让 我发生 的事情
sort of less depressed about the future
对未来 不那么沮丧
so to speak is that at any given time in
可以这么说 ，在 任何 特定的时间
history you know you can still have
你知道你仍然可以拥有的历史
meaningful purposes even though they may
有意义的目的， 即使他们可能
not look meaningful from a different
从 另一个 看起来并不有意义
point in history and that there's sort
在历史中指出 并且有点排序
of a whole theory you can kind of build
你可以建立一个完整的理论
up based on kind of the the trajectories
基于轨迹的种类
that you've followed through the space
你已经穿过了这个空间
of purposes and sort of interesting if
目的和有趣的如果
you can't jump like you say let's get
你不能像你说的那样跳起来
chronically frozen for a you know 300
长期冷冻，你知道300
years and then you know be be back again
多年，然后你知道 会 再回来
the the interesting cases then you know
你 知道 的那些有趣的案例
are the purposes that you sort of you
有目的，你 那种你
know that you find yourself in ones that
知道你发现自己处于那种状态
have any continuity with what we know
与我们所知道的有任何连续性
today
今天
I should stop with that that's a
我应该停下来那是一个
beautiful way to end it
结束它的美丽方式
they Han
他们汉
[Applause]
[掌声]